Nvidia just booked [music] $96.2 billion
in revenue in a single quarter.
>> Isn't that a closed loop circular
economy? Couldn't that collapse? Every
economy is circular in nature. [music]
To the extent there is an elephant in
this particular room, that would be the
ex [music] safety team conducted an
investigation into suspected Chinese
inauthentic accounts. We identified a
bot farm [music] of approximately
200,000 accounts. These posts contain
claims that AI data centers are driving
up household electricity prices [music]
and straining the grid.
>> Shocked. Shocked. I say that there are
foreign influence operations attempting
to suppress American AI data center
deployment. Shocked.
>> The difficult [music] part is we have
really no easy defense against it.
>> Open AI released the first [music]
performances of their chip Jalapino.
OpenAI is no longer just a customer of
Nvidia. They're becoming a chip
designer.
>> Inference is moving off of Nvidia for
sure. This is the first 2x of a 100x
performance gains. [music]
>> We're in such a crazy future where I
could imagine a world where say an open
AI compute cloud hosts an anthropic
model and open AAI and anthropic win at
the same time. [music]
>> Now that's a moonshot ladies and
gentlemen.
>> Welcome to Moonshots everyone. Your
number one podcast on all things AI and
exponential. Your front row seat to the
incredible accelerating singularity. I
hope you can feel it like we all do. You
know, guys, we just recorded two days
ago and it feels like a lifetime ago.
>> I can't believe it.
>> Isn't it?
>> I mean, every story we're going through
today is is new information in the last
two days. It's crazy.
>> It is like the
>> It's the podcasting singularity. Peter,
>> it really is. Well, guys, I'm here with
my incredible uh my original four
moonshot magnificent mates, Alex Weer
Gross, our in-house ASI. And you know
the question, Alex, is are you real?
Well, if people come to the Moonshots
live event, uh they'll have a chance to
evaluate your flesh and bloodness. Uh
>> maybe that's the one question that I
get.
>> Alex, [laughter]
>> that's the one.
>> Everyone can copy you, Peter, and pinch
my cheeks.
>> Yeah, exactly. [laughter]
>> Uh Dave Blondon, our empressario of AI
investing. And and Dave, you're going to
be running a session on AI investing at
Moonshots Live, which is going to be
very good.
>> And Sel is our global globe trotder. Our
Where's Waldo? You're back from uh from
Brazil.
>> I'm back uh 36 hours in Brazil and back.
I've probably got one of the worst
carbon footprints anywhere right now.
>> Are you leaving tomorrow for like Japan
or
>> No, I'm here for a few days. Um uh and
then I've got an overnight next week.
It's not so bad. All right.
>> We should make you be be like Bill Gates
and buy carbon offsets for all the all
the emissions from [laughter] your
flight. That would cost
>> I'll plant a tree in every airport uh uh
front lawn that I get to.
>> Uh I'm Peter Diamandis, your host and
optimism provocator. So much happening
in the last two days. You know, we've
reviewed 200 plus stories. I get a
download from my AI and from Alex, my
other AI [laughter]
every day. Uh we've narrowed it down to
about 15 today that are fun. I I would
categorize these stories as provocative
um like massively impactful and bizarre.
That's sort of my my summary. You know,
our missions all at once.
>> All at once. Yeah, for sure. Our mission
here is keep you optimistic and ready
for the supersonic tsunami that is
heading our way. If you're new to
moonshots, welcome. A pleasure to have
you. You know, our mission here is keep
you informed of what just happened and
where things are going. If you're a
regular, a fellow moonshot, welcome
back. Uh let me share a slide here
because I want to invite people to two
specific elements here. Um the first is
we're going to be having a moonshots AMA
uh over Zoom. We're inviting
[clears throat] all of you our listeners
to join us. We're going to be doing it
twice in September. Uh once in the
morning so that people in Europe and
Asia can easily join. Once in the
evening so people in the east coast and
in the US can join. Uh we want to we
want to meet you. Uh you know we don't
get a chance to answer all your
questions. So uh you're going to have a
shot at you know grilling Alex Dave See
and myself on this. So
>> I love these units too because we get to
we get to hear what what's on
everybody's mind. It's never obvious to
me what people are thinking because
there's so much impact from all this
change and but it it affects different
people differently. So it's really nice
to get a sample of what's going through
everybody's brain.
>> Yeah, for sure. And you know, you can
tell us whether you, you know, whether
you want it once a week, twice a week,
continuous in Alex's living room.
[laughter]
Uh, and also on the screen here, our new
X handle, uh, is moonshots_pod.
So, please follow us on X as well. You
know, we're putting up our clips. We're
putting up the full podcast as a chance
for you to have it on your feed instead
of just on YouTube. So, uh, shall we get
into it, gentlemen?
>> Absolutely.
>> All right. a lot to cover today. So, I'm
going to open with a few AI stories as
we normally do. Uh, so Nvidia is on
fire. Nvidia just booked 96.2 billion in
revenue in a single quarter. I mean,
this is more than the GDP of of the
majority of the countries on the planet.
Up 106% year-over-year with guidance for
the current quarter of another 10%
higher, 108 billion. For context, that
is more than a billion dollars per day.
Crazy.
>> You know, further Jensen's guidance for
2028 is 70% growth against Wall Street's
consensus of 44%. You know, Jensen
called the Frontier Labs quote, "The
first generation of startups that needed
tens of billions of dollars of compute
to get to their product." Crazy. Um, in
related news, Elon Musk is making some
bold predictions about SpaceX revenues.
We've heard him in the past say that
he's going to in the last earnings call
he's going to reach a trillion dollars
in revenue by 2030 potentially 2029. Now
yesterday Elon tweeted that he may well
reach 3.5 trillion in revenue in 2033.
You know uh by reference the company
today with the highest revenue is Amazon
at $828 billion just to give it some
context for Elon's 3.5 trillion. Uh Dave
let me go to you first. you know, is is
Nvidia's revenue growth sustainable or
is this just, you know, the peak here?
What do you think about that?
>> Actually, it's a really interesting two
forks in the road here. Nvidia has a lot
of vulnerabilities and it'll come up
later in the pod, but at the same time,
they're going to be sold out for as far
as the I can see no matter what. So, I
think that everyone's got to use Nvidia
for training neural nets. It's the it's,
you know, 90% of the revenue, 95% of the
profits. And, you know, these revenues
are not just revenues. These are 80 to
85% gross margin revenues. The
profitability of this company has never
been seen before on the face of the
earth.
>> And to the extent but but everybody's
vulnerable too, you know, because all
the major companies, all the
magnumobstas are starting to overlap so
much in what they do.
>> So the biggest vulnerability at Nvidia
by far is TSMC is still their one and
only manufacturer of everything they
sell.
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, have you ever seen
>> I'm amazed they haven't vertically
integrated or haven't tried to like Elon
is.
>> Well, I mean, but they're they're it's
tricky because if they were to try and
build their own fabs, they'd have to do
it very quietly and sneakily because
they cannot piss off TSMC. You know,
they're about a third of TSMC's
manufacturing goes to Nvidia, you know,
and another third roughly goes to Apple
and the the whole rest of the world gets
the other third. But you can't you can't
rock that boat, uh, you know, casually.
You have to do it very sneakily. Um, and
you know, as Alex has said on many
podcasts, there's new physics and new
new uh technology is going to come
through AI imminently, which could
disrupt the entire manufacturing supply
chain, how chips are made, what they're
made of. And so there's just so much
change coming. So, so Nvidia is making
all kinds of moves to shore up its
position while it's on top of the world.
Uh, and and you know, you almost can't
spend the money fast enough at the rate
that it's coming in. I mean, you know, I
was talking talking to my kids about,
well, with so many of our portfolio
companies, I I'll meet with them weekly
and they'll say, "Oh, I had a meeting
with a manufacturer in Vermont. I had a
meeting with this, you know, with JP
Morgan." Like, why are you meeting with
anyone anyone other than Jensen or one
of the other Magnum Mobster companies or
one of their satellites? Like, it's
insane. The amount of money pouring
through just that funnel dwarfs the
entire rest of the economy. and and your
success and failure is intimately tied
to just that one thing and everything
else is just a distraction. So, you
know, Jensen is is he's pouring out
money in checks of 5 billion here, 12
billion there, 20 billion there and and
if you're if you're not in that flow of
conversations, you're not in the most
relevant conversation in the world in
the history.
>> One second. Let me let me call him one
second. I need some more capital.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Exactly. And you know, if
you can't get Jensen, just get one of
his E staff. There's only what 20 25
people in that list. Talk to them.
>> Alex, what do you make of this?
>> Yeah, I'd be the last person to suggest
that this is one big wash trade uh
circular financing scheme, but I I do
wonder but but but but I I do wonder the
extent to which the financial markets
have fully priced in Nvidia's financing
of their customers. I I guess that's
that to the extent there is an elephant
in this particular room that would be it
and I I think it would be it would sure
be swell as a participant in the
financial markets to have clearer
distinction between how much of this
demand is Nvidia financed demand or not.
If it turns out that a disproportionate
amount of this demand is directly or
indirectly backstopped or financed or
credited by Nvidia through one or more
intermediaries, then I I think that
starts to look a little bit too bubbly,
which I I'm not thrilled with at all.
I'd like to see no hiccups in this
singularity. I I would not like to
discover 2 to 3 years from now that some
of uh some or a large portion of all of
this demand at the infra layer was being
artificially propped up through
financial engineering. I think that
would be like a highly sub-optimal
outcome. I I still think even if it
turned out that some quantum of the
demand, the exploding demand that we're
seeing is being artificially inflated
through financial engineering, I my my
forecast, this is not an investment
advice, but my forecast is, you know, at
most a mini winter as it were because I
think compute is fundamentally
substituting for real estate and human
labor and other [clears throat] raw
inputs as the fundamental substrate for
human civil ization. But I when I see
nosebleleed growth numbers like this and
I see a bunch of other headlines, Nvidia
financing a bunch of data center
deployments, I I have just like in full
transparency, I have a little bit of a
tickle at this point in the back of my
mind how much of this is financial
engineering.
>> Nice. Hey, See, are you seeing the same
videos on X that I am like from Ray
Dallio and other financial leaders
saying, you know, I'm out of the
markets. You know, this is, you know,
our the PE ratios are off the charts
and, you know, there's this level of of
fear-mongering in the in the financial
markets. At the same time, you're seeing
this massive growth and and there's like
where do you go? You know, do you stay
fully in? Do you jump out? How do you
think about it? This is this is a
classic dilemma, right? You got to hedge
your bets in this model. I think Alex
makes a really great point. The circular
revenue is very concerning. Um I love
the way you say it, Alex. It would be
swell if it wasn't it was all ticky
boots.
>> I don't want this to be financial. I
don't want this to be a bubble. I really
don't need bubbles.
>> I totally understand it. It would be
really bad if the whole thing collapsed
and then we were in a in a dead period
for a period of time and that just slows
civilization down dramatically and that
would be a bad thing. you're better off
having steady uh regular growth where
the market has time to self-correct in
the new structures and we don't have
that right now. Things are kind of going
vertical. But from what there's a couple
of things happening that I found
interesting. One is what's clear is
Nvidia is trying to move out of just
being a chip company to trying to become
like literally an operating system for
the whole of intelligence. Right? I
thought the hugging face acquisition was
super smart.
>> And so that's just that's a still a
rumor, right? But
>> do we know
Yes, if if it's it's uh alleged, shall
we say, right? But this is this reminds
me of being as clever as Microsoft uh
buying GitHub, right? Um and can I tell
a quick story about this?
>> Of course.
>> Um so Microsoft tries to acquire GitHub,
which was less than 10 years old for
$7.5 billion. Okay. The CFO and freak
and the corp dev people start freaking
out going, "The company has barely any
assets. It has barely any workforce. it
has barely any intellectual property.
What the hell are we buying here? Right?
What do I put on the balance sheet? And
they were literally trying to kill the
transaction until Satya said, "Listen,
we're buying 30 million developers
loyalty because that's how many people
use GitHub at the time." Uh and and so
we overrode that and and they got it
done. Uh now as we move into this AI
world, GitHub turned out to be one of
the smartest things they could have ever
have done because [clears throat] it
gave them uh access into all of that
open-source thinking and access to all
of that stuff. The same thing is
happening if this acquisition happens.
You're buying the community and that's a
very classic exo play to do this. To
your broader point, Peter, about are we
in a bubble, etc. I think there's some
macro things happening that are much
more concerning. for example, we're
printing money like it's going out of
style and I think that has a bigger
chance of collapsing the markets than
anything else. What's happening with the
bond markets and Japan and stuff is
absolutely insane uh in terms of the
circular chaos in the fiat currency
world, but that's a different
discussion.
>> Yeah. So, let me let me jump to the uh
SpaceX story of Elon projecting 3.5
trillion by 2033.
Um Dave and Alex, love your your points
on this.
Well,
>> well, I mean, for starters, you you said
it up front. No company in the history
of the world has ever gotten to a
trillion.
>> Yeah.
>> In revenue, and that includes massive
massive companies like Amazon and
Walmart, uh 3.5 trillion. But, you know,
Elon's always been right before. He's
often been wrong by a couple years in
the timeline, but not not because of
anything other than barriers that didn't
need to exist. You know, engineering
mistakes, regulatory barriers, whatever.
So he always says look this is the
native size of the opportunity and this
is the best case timeline and then the
size always turns out to be right and
the timeline is off by a couple years
because of unforeseen delays. So I have
no reason to believe he's wrong about
the 3.5 trillion but the scale of that
relative to anything in history is just
it's just mind-boggling.
>> Alex,
>> yeah I I think Elon tends to like to
move in three-dimensional ways. So
again, without this being misconstrued
as any sort of investment advice, I
think there is a path to that, but I
think it's a highly nonlinear
multi-dimensional path. I I think the
most obvious path to get there is one,
SpaceX and Tesla merge sometime in the
next sometime in the next year or two.
And that gives SpaceX, the new SpaceX,
not the old SpaceX, Optimus revenue. I
think Optimus alone, not financial
advice, could be a multi-t trillion
dollar per year business. And then the
cloud, uh SpaceX offering hyperscaler
services, which last I checked were the
majority of its revenue growth in the
past few months, could continue to grow
its hyperscaler business both
terrestrially, which is where it is now,
and soon the Dyson swarm. I think the
Dyson swarm alone could probably
generate trillions of dollars in
revenue. I I think Starlink probably I
in the face of Optimus and the Dyson
swarm. I think Starlink probably ends up
being rounding error. I think cars are
rounding error. I think applications
which interestingly in the SpaceX S1
SpaceX went on and on and on about uh
digital optimists and applications and
the service economy maybe seems
unlikely. I I think the core strength of
Elon's ecosystem is less application
layer and more physical infrastructure.
So if they just totally dominate robots
and uh orbital data center infra, I I
think that's probably a few trillion
dollars.
>> I mean SpaceX is my largest financial
bet right now, full disclosure. And I
think about it as a way of, you know, if
you're if you're investing in OpenAI or
Anthropic, it's a, you know, a single
layer bet. You're betting on the models.
Um, but SpaceX is everything. It's it's
ultimately chips and data centers and
models and comms and infrastructure and
launch and you get a chance to bet on
all of them. Um, you know, I think the
biggest risk is just Elon being around
long enough to implement his his vision.
So, I know he's probably walking around
with an army of guards. When I when I
see him on occasion, uh, it doesn't look
that way. So, I I hope he's got the
proper protection. For our listeners
here, Dave, you know, the question of
how do they, you know, we're not a
financial show, but, you know, we're
throwing around massive numbers here.
And how do you, you know, how do you
think about playing this this market?
Um, staying in it, doubling down,
hedging against it. What's your,
>> you know, it's it's actually, I think in
some senses getting easier to understand
because everything that's going on, you
know, you can you can start to
understand it from just two things. AI
training and AI inference. And you know
what what Elon is putting into space is
purely inference. you know, all the
satellites, all the revenue is going to
be from Starlink, which is about
connecting AI generated video and other
AI generated content to everybody on the
planet, but also the AI data centers are
going to dwarf everything that Elon's
launched so far. It's just inference
time data center in space. But that's
inference only. You know, the the
training time is a very different beast.
That's where Nvidia is just going to
kill it because for training time, you
need all the GPUs to be coherent in one
location like Tennessee. you know, you
need 100 thousand and ultimately a
million and then, you know, probably
several million NVIDIA GPUs to be in
this kind of very tight all collect
cluster that can that can train the next
generation of models. But at inference
time, it can be spread all over the
world, all over space. And so those are
very very different emerging market.
Even the chips are going to be very
different for those two markets. And
then everything else kind of falls out
from that. You're like, well, what's
sustainable and investable? Robotics is
is sustainable, investable, but only if
you have great AI at designing robots.
You know, the idea that you can build a
better robotics company without great
inference time models that are specific
to manufacturing to design, you'll never
sustain it. So then you start to see all
these great investments in all these
vertical markets like drug discovery and
robotics, but they're all also built
around proprietary inference time models
that are very good at that use case.
Mhm. So all everything else looks like
it's going to like SAS software and
everything. It's going to be undisrupted
for a while, but that's a choice that
Elon and Daario have made to not disrupt
all those voters and kind of leave it
alone. And [clears throat] so you like
Alex was saying earlier, it looks a lot
like the AI economy is a circular
economy where Jensen is putting money
into data centers. The data centers are
buying the chips that's providing
inference to the vertical use case
companies. Isn't that a closed loop
circular economy? Couldn't that
collapse? But to me, it looks more like
imagine there's a civilization on Alpha
Centauri and they've discovered super
intelligence.
What are they going to do? They're going
to they're going to build this massive
valuable economy within themselves. Are
they going to trade with Earth? They're
not going to give a rat's ass about
Earth. It's too far away. It's so slow.
And that's exactly what's happening in
the new AI economy. So, every economy is
circular in nature. You know, dollars
just move in a circle. you know, euros
move in a circle. So now the circle is
tightening up to being this new economy
only cares about itself and cares very
little about the legacy economy. And so
you know I talked to my brother you know
over at Bestark who works with Fidelity
and America prize and UBS and his
initial reaction a year ago was like you
know AI will not really have hit until I
see it show up at Fidelity. Now he's
like, you know what, it doesn't care. It
literally doesn't care when it's
discovering new medicines and new
physics. And you know, we already
mentioned that OMPic and Mangaro are
bigger than all of AI inference
combined, just just one drug discovery.
So if it comes up with five or 10 more
drug discoveries, which it inevitably
will very soon, the amount of revenue
flowing back into the AI economy from
just that will dwarf the legacy world. I
have a I have a similar metaphor that
may that I think about right when you
look at the internet in the introduction
of the internet in the early days when
Google started uh AdSense and Adwords
and whatever people are like yeah um um
it's this thing that will add create
some value but little by little it
sucked up all the revenue in the entire
advertising industry almost completely
and I think of AI in a similar way it
starts off kind of being a little bit
cir circular but little by little it
sucks up more and more uh interest uh in
the whole economy. Um something big
happened with uh um the legal firm uh
can't remember the name that they just
bought. They just figure out how to buy
this. You look at Google buying Spirit
Airlines data, right? Little by little
we're going to find ways where AI is
going to start sucking up all of the
data in other industries to use in
powerful ways and then create business
models around that. So I I look at it
from that perspective. But in general
that I think the approach your the way
you think about it is also very
accurate.
>> Well there are these meta signals these
high level you know kind of orthogonal
signals like if I ask somebody who's an
entrepreneur uh do you know how to train
a foundation model? Do you know how to
fine-tune one? Uh do you listen to the
Moonshots podcast? Every single one of
them goes up 10, 20, 100x in value in
some cases, you know, up to a thousandx
returns on those deals. No losers yet.
Zero. 0.00 failures. So I don't need to
be a rocket scientist to say like and
then somebody says, "Well, I'm not
really I'm I'm more of an application
layer guy and you know I'm more of a
vibe coder guy." Like okay, lots of
losers in that bucket. So it's like like
just do you really understand what's
going on? Do you listen to Alex and what
he's about to say? If yes, you will
succeed.
>> Alex,
>> close us out on this one. Alex,
>> I I think the I I think there's probably
an important just on the financial
engineering and circular economy side. I
think there are perhaps two different
forms of circular economy one can have.
So in one form of circular economy, you
have company A selling goods to company
B and company B buying or selling goods
back to company A. Call it an income
statement based circular economy. and in
balance like yeah you don't want
circular or wash trades uh that are
overly engineered to inflate revenue
there either but maybe call that a
slightly from a bubble perspective
slightly more healthful form of circular
economy then maybe there's a slightly in
this context less healthful form of
circularity which would be company A is
using not its income statement but its
balance sheet in the form of private
credit loans etc to finance the purchase
of by company B of company A's goods and
right now as just a again not financial
advice but as a shareholder of the
entire market via lowcost broad index
funds I don't feel like I have
tremendous visibility into which of
those two forms of circularity we're
seeing at the very heart of the
innermost loop and I would love more
clarity this episode is sponsored by
Google for startups [music] think about
this for a second you now have access to
the same generative AI models that cost
hundreds of millions of dollars to
train. Google's startup technical guide
for generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google DeepMinds
models in production. Images, video,
audio, all of it. Real architecture,
real results. Find the link in the show
notes below.
All right, I'm going to move us on to
our next uh two stories that are coming
out of China in the world of video
production. The first story is the roll
out of Juan 3.0 by Alibaba. Juan 3 is
capable of generating 30-cond single
pass videos from documents,
spreadsheets, slides, and web pages. I
wonder what kind of a video you get out
of a a spreadsheet. Uh, their API runs
between 5 cents to 20 cents per second
of generated video. That's something
like 20K to 60K for a 90-minute film,
right? These prices are beginning to
collapse. Uh this is one day after
announcing their largest ever private
follow-on offering by a Hong Kong listed
company at 10.2 billion. Clearly they're
engineering uh their stock price. So
that's Juan 3.0 is the first story. The
second story comes from Runway's
co-founder who reports that video
generation now represents roughly 70%
of all AI token consumption in China
driven by short form content and
robotics. And it's the you know it's
growing faster than claude code grew in
the US. Uh the framing here is that
America is LLM pill large language model
pled and China is world model pill. And
the implications of that are that the
two superpowers are fundamentally having
different priorities. So America is
building large language models, China is
building world models. The language
models predict the next token. The world
models are predicting the next state of
reality. So uh you know these these
large these world models are
particularly going to be important
besides for video generation also for
robotics autonomous driving physics
simulations and videogen. Uh so Alex go
to you first on this uh your thoughts on
3 and the 70% you know video token
consumption. Crazy.
>> I I agree with the sentiment. I think
it's striking and I have a unified field
theory that would explain it. My unified
field theory is that American AI labs
are revenue maxing and Chinese AI labs
are not. So when Open AI tried tried to
to be in the video gen business, they
ended up abandoning it because Anthropic
ran away with their lunch by revenue per
token maxing with codegen which is call
it a more LLM shaped use case for their
compute. the Chinese labs really I mean
yes they're generating revenue yes
they're IPOing yes they're growing
quickly but really they're not revenue
maxing they're giving away model weights
for free you don't revenue max by giving
your model weights away for free so if
you're not in the business of maximizing
revenue per token then you might as well
be spending tokens on video versus more
economically productive applications
that that's my unified field theory for
why you see so much world model
inference in China and relatively little
by comparison from American Labs.
American labs are too busy doing more
economically productive applications.
>> Alex, which one gets us to AGI faster?
>> Um, well, it's a trick question because
I think we hit AGI no later than summer
of 2020 with LLM. With LLM, we didn't
have good video models,
>> which progresses us from AGI towards ASI
faster world.
>> We already have ASI. Trick question
again. I I I don't buy the premise,
Peter. I don't buy the premise that we
don't already have super intelligence.
You could ask like an adjacent question
which is which uh in the long term
whatever is left of the long term which
advances the capability frontier most
effectively world models
>> or text based models
>> so moved to ask that question.
[laughter]
>> Okay. So I'll ask myself that question
that the answer is I I think in the end
omnimodal models are the best. I I see
like Fable 5 is so strong and yet its
visual capabilities and visual reasoning
capabilities are so weak and I think
that in the medium-term which is like 6
to 12 months I think that's an
impairment that hopefully Anthropic is
busy repairing with M&A activities but I
I think they're on a collision
trajectory and whether we get diffusion
transformers at the end of the day or
some sort of hybrid model that
hybridizes the best of vision and video
and audio with autogress aggressive
textbased gen. I think they have to
combine one way or another.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
Dave, any thoughts?
>> I Yeah, big time. And you're going to
have to shut me up on this topic, so
just fair warning. But um everything
Alex said is dead right, of course. Uh
but I think there's a story within the
story there where look, the Chinese uh
they don't have the ability to sell
Kimmy or Quen into the enterprise use
case because nobody knows if they can
trust it. And video is perfectly
profitable. It's a it's a fantastic way
to take your maybe not trustworthy
model, get it to market and generate
huge amounts of revenue and huge value,
but I don't think that world models
versus, you know, language models, you
know, which is going to recursively
self-improve first. I think it's just
purely about smarter engineers with
plenty of cash and lots of training
chips, uh, working on the problem.
That's the race. And so, the Chinese are
brilliant by going after video because
they can just launch it on the world.
It's a global product. No one's worried
about security in that use case and it
just generates tons of revenue. But
remember, OpenAI was ahead of them and
decided not to invest in it anymore
because the enterprise use case is so
much more valuable. So America's taking
kind of the highbrow road. You know,
let's solve real business problems, cure
real diseases. It's more profitable. It,
you know, maximizes revenue per token.
So it's better in that sense anyway. But
at the end of the day, it's all about
that revenue pouring back into more and
more training chips that turn into, you
know, better and bigger, you know, 10
trillion and then 20 trillion parameter
models that then get distilled. And so
that's what's kicking off RSI. And I'll
tell you what else, Demis was the first
guy to really think this through, but he
couldn't act on it at Google. It's too
bureaucratic. Daario took it and he's
the first guy that said, "We don't care
about consumer movies, videos, whatever.
We care about a model that can improve
itself through better code and better
training ideas. That's all we're going
to focus on. If we can productize that
at the same time, great. But at the end
of the day, that's going to recursively
self-improve first, and that's what's
going to get ahead ahead of everybody
else. And the Chinese believe the same
exact thing.
>> I miss Sora, by the way. It was so much
fun with my kids.
>> It was fun.
>> Uh,
>> I think Sora will be back, Peter. I of
course gone for long.
>> Yeah. See, um, what do you think about
the idea of of 70% of the tokens being
spent on on video out of China? Is there
an implication there for us?
>> Well, I think there's there's a couple
of things going on here. I I think Dave
nailed it what what he with what he said
in terms of are you going for RSI or are
you going for kind of like world models,
right? And what's happening right now is
you've got the US optimizing around
software engineers and and knowledge
work. uh and China is optimizing and
heading towards manufacturing and
commerce and media and and to some
extent some of the machines like the
robots etc. eventually you're going to
converge, right? The winning systems,
you're going to have uh language and
vision and and uh all of this memory uh
uh strung together. Um
the future, if I think about the future
of AI, AGI, ASI, it's where you hit the
physical world that you're going to make
the biggest difference, right? Rob, uh
humanoid robots or other form robots.
Cough, cough. Um, I think the
intelligence that can model and then
manipulate the world and act inside the
world is going to win. In that case, I
think where China's heading may have a
slightly better advantage. But if we get
um Anthropic or one of these guys to
RSI, then I think Dave is correct. That
kind of trumps everything and that'll be
the inner loop that just swallows a
whole bunch of other stuff. So, you
could go either way here.
>> You know, we had a conversation uh last
week with ImmOD. And by the way to all
our listeners, Immad sent his regrets.
He was supposed to be here at last
minute travel. Uh where he made the
point, I think very importantly that AI
is one of the most persuasive agents out
there. The ability to understand a
person and persuade a person and
videogen combined with AI is a very
powerful force and it's a force for
spreading culture. And so the question
becomes, you know, with China about to
become, if they're not already, the
dominant world producer of video
content, right, in any language, on any
per on any, you know, topic. Um, you
know, what are the implications of that?
>> Oh my god, they're they're huge. They're
crazy. My youngest son, Jack, actually
told me this morning that he he turned
off Instagram. He just deleted it from
his phone.
>> And all the kids had already gotten rid
of Tik Tok. But the the suggestion
engine is so good and it just sucks you
in and before you know it an hour of
doom scrolling has gone by and you're
like oh my god what am I doing here?
>> But you know the Chinese you heard Alvin
Grlin on the podcast say that you know
in China they banned everything. You
can't show blood in a in a video. You
can't show blood in a in a video game.
The blood comes out green. like, okay,
well, if they're allowed to ban that
level of detail, they're going to
control all of these actions and try and
prevent their children from being sucked
into the vortex. Meanwhile, they're
perfectly happy to sell it to every
other country in the world and generate
that revenue. But I I got to imagine the
CCP is sitting there saying, "Wow, these
guys are just suckers. We can launch any
AI generated influence machine on any
country, completely change the national
opinion and turn the dials here from
from Beijing and they don't seem to be
able to do anything about it. They've
all got free speech and whatever and
they can't they can't protect themselves
at all.
>> But these these AI agents are so good. I
mean, they're going to get smarter and
smarter and smarter and user specific.
That's the new thing.
>> Dave, that brings us to the to the next
story outside of China. Um, and it's an
extremely important story for America uh
to hear loud and clear and especially
for any parents listening. So, China is
tightening restrictions on AI companions
amid concerns that users are developing
emotional dependence on virtual
partners. Uh, they're going to in, you
know, prohibit AI companion services for
minors and restrict the use for adults.
So the regulations come out of policy
makers as they grapple with the
loneliness epidemic that's there, you
know, alongside falling marriage rates,
right? The one child policy really
devastated China. Um, and the concern
here is that people are forming
emotional bonds with AIS that substitute
for human relations and the substitution
is accelerating and it's a demographic
crisis. You know, we've already pointed
on the pod that much of the world is now
below the 2.1 children per family
required to sustain a country's
population. You know, worst among them
are South Korea. That's down to 0.75
children per family. South Korea is
evaporating. Singapore is at, you know,
roughly one child per family, as is
Ukraine, and China's at one child per
family still even after they removed
that that that uh ban. So, you know,
China's becoming the first regulated uh
first country to regulate against AI
companions. You know, my bet is Japan,
Singapore, Korea is going to follow
closely. And this raises the question
for every country, not just China. You
know, what happens to society when the
easiest emotional connection you can
make is to your AI and not to another
human.
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah.
>> It's crazy. You know, Peter, do you
remember Boris Zelman from MIT?
>> Bio biology. He was actually uh his dad
was in charge of food science at General
Foods. He invented the c coffee crystal.
>> Okay.
>> Um but you know he was like you know
what we all know that smoking is
addictive now. And then smoking took
over the entire country then took over
the world and then we said oh my god
this is killing everybody. And then we
stopped and then we did the same with
junk food. you know, junk food is so but
he could develop a food at General Foods
that was so delicious, a French fry
coating that is so delicious that you
just cannot physically resist it and
then the whole country is, you know,
diabetes.
>> Um, so we do this habitually and we
react to it like 10, 20, 30 years later
and then we correct it reactively.
>> But if we start rolling out addictive
AI, uh, and and then we say, well, the
government will wake up when there's a
crisis, but that crisis is when a whole
generation of kids is wrecked.
>> Yeah. Yeah, but you cannot afford the
20-year delay with this particular
topic.
>> I mean, the the you know, the shout out
to parents is please be careful. Um, you
know, you form normal social
relationships in your teens. Uh, Salem,
you're a father of a 15-year-old. How do
you think about this?
you know, if you step back, um, the
right regulatory structure is probably
some level of transparency and consent
and figuring out what is the types of
harm that could be done and then
mitigating them, right? Um, trying to
having a government decide what
relationships are authentic or not is
going to be very tricky because which is
this is what's happening right now. Um
we've got we're gone from regulating
from what AI says in the China case to
saying regulating how attached are you
to become to it, right? Um and so this
is a totally new regulatory frontier.
Social media was very very addictive
because an algorithm as Dave points out
can learn your intimate habits and
without you realizing uh totally capture
you and that's really really bad. All
the kids are completely addicted to
social media today and banning it
outright is pretty much the only
problem, the only way because all their
neoortexes are forming at a time when
they're getting totally addicted to
stuff and it's going to ruin them
structurally for a long time and then
you need a lot of um kind of fixes to
that. The the the broader picture though
I don't know how to think about that
like we are we are uh we are dropping on
the child care or the childbearing side.
so dramatically that this is a huge
structural challenge for civilization,
right? How do you navigate that is going
to be really really tough. There's also
other issues in all this. The privacy
issue, right? Your companion AI is going
to know so much more intimacy about you
than you do. That's kind of and then
there's the b there's the benefit side.
there are some really solid benefits
around loneliness, disability, elderly
companions, um, uh, therapeutics, uh,
and and and coaching, social skills,
right? So, you can't just you shouldn't
just categorize the whole thing as
pathological. It's the standard problem
we have with any technology is how do
you extract the promise without the
peril?
>> Yeah.
>> And that's the challenge for regulatory
across the board.
>> Alex, I'd love your views here, Pel.
>> Yeah. I have a bit of perhaps a
contrarian perspective on this. I I
think the Chinese Communist Party is
actually going to do an about face
sometime in the next year or two or
three and decide that they actually love
AI companions. And the reason is it's
another method for party control. If you
can make sure that all of these AI
companions go through all of your
ideological filters and become a little
bit more like a CCP version of Neil
Stevenson's A Young Lady's Illustrated
Primmer and a little bit less like some
sort of distractant, I I think the
party, this is a prediction, I think the
party decides actually having everyone
or maybe not everyone but a sizable
fraction of the youth of China deeply
engaged with party deeply controlled AI
companions is actually from the party's
perspective net helpful not net harmful
and I I think so my forecast here would
be that once the CCP has decided that it
has a way to steer the country's youth
via AI companions it will decide no
actually we like these AI companions
after all
>> but bring it home Alex what do you think
about here in the US
and AI companions
>> the there US states that are already
trying to regulate these things out of
existence and trying to to ban romantic
relationships between America's youth
and AI. I'd like to think that in this
country we enjoy enough freedoms that
they won't succeed. Uh I'm just reminded
again one of my operational definitions
of the singularity is every sci-fi trope
everywhere all at once. And I I can't
shake out of my head the famous uh from
Futurama, don't date robots. I I I think
I I think different countries will react
in different ways and my forecast for
the US is you may see individual states
maybe it'll be a federalist issue where
some states ban them and some states
don't question mark as to whether we end
up with a national policy on romance
with AI companions but if I had to bet
my bet is that at least in some places
in the US AI companionship including
romantic companionship including robotic
romantic companionship will be legal.
That's my bet.
>> Yeah, we're going to talk at the end of
this pod a story about robotic sex
partners just to spice it up.
>> The the place to watch on this is Japan
because they tend to be much more
tolerant of this type of stuff. There's
already a case where a Japanese woman is
marrying an AI uh and they're like,
"Okay, go." Uh so we'll see this play
out, I think, there first. Well, South
Korea
is
South Korea is is super high-tech
>> and a very early adopter of everything
without a lot of regulation and they
have all kinds of the lowest birth rate
in the world. Uh one of the highest
suicide rates in the world just all
kinds of issues.
>> Yeah. Maybe two two
>> two points. One, I have difficult time
getting myself worked up over collapse
of human population. I I think we're so
many decades at this point past the
limits of growth which I I view as like
nonsensical propaganda at at this point.
The world we like humanity would be fine
uh barring some total disaster. Uh we
have a carrying capacity in the tens of
billions if we use just the earth that
we have correctly. We can also survive
with an enormous amount of AI and
automation with fewer people. So I I one
area where I perhaps differ from Elon
sort of uh virolently pro-atalist
policy. I I think the world is going to
be fine regardless of whether we have
more people on margin or fewer people on
margin. We're going to have so much AI
in the solar system. I I just I don't
think it's going to be a major X- risk
at all.
>> Yeah.
>> I got to say something here.
>> Please go ahead.
>> Um uh in a rare moment I'm 100% aligned
with you, Alex. I don't
>> This is a rare moment.
>> I think that it's here and there you and
I have opposing points, but this one I'm
absolutely 100% with you on this is this
is uh trying to worry about how many
kids we're going to have. It's going to
end up however it ends up.
>> Listen, the the the challenge is to a
country like South Korea, it's it's
sublimating. It's evaporating. Uh and if
all of a sudden, you know, the
population is dropping smaller and
smaller, you're losing the culture
there. And that's that's the issue. And
I hate it when people I'm giving a
presentation on longevity and people
say, "Oh my god, can the world sustain,
you know, uh people enough people when
it when people are growing to 150 years
old?" It's like, uh, you know, look at
the actual numbers. Um, for sure we need
people to
>> I also don't I I it's an interesting
point. I I don't think we lose culture
if population on the margin not like
catastrophic nuclear war but on the
margin if population goes down if if
these cultures are centuries old when
populations were smaller I think it
follows reasonably that if the
population on margin halves the culture
will still be there in one form or
another but the reality is we're going
to have so much again AI the AI is being
trained off of our culture anyway
>> all right moving us along this is a
story, Alex, that uh that you fed me and
and it's a fun it's a fun one. So, our
next story is about a company called
Flock Safety. It's one of the fastest
growing public safety tech companies in
the US. Flock was founded back in 2017.
What is that, 9 years ago? And its core
product is a network of AI powered
license plate reading cameras used by
the police department, neighborhoods,
schools, and businesses to identify
vehicles associated with crimes and
missing persons. The company has further
expanded its platforms to include video
cameras, shotgun and audio detection,
mobile surveillance trailers, drones,
and software that ties all these feeds
together. Flock says its systems are
used by more than 6,000 communities
across 49 states, generating over 20
billion vehicle scans per month. So, let
me show a video here uh that Alex
provided me. This is out of San Diego uh
where Darth Vader is is testifying on
behalf of Flock. Take a look at this.
>> The Emperor is a fan of Flock and we
must continue utilizing Flock
technologies so that we can follow and
surveil the rebel scum as they move from
playground to playground, from
playground to pool, from pool to
gymnasium. Because we all know that the
flock cameras are not only following the
license plate readers. They are
following children. They are following
children in parks and gymnasiums. And we
need this. I need this so I can stalk my
exgirlfriend.
>> Okay. So, uh, Alex, let's go to you
first on this one.
>> I think this honestly I think this is
the face of AI at the municipal level at
this point. We we talk all of the time
about the implications of AI for
enterprise use cases, for transformative
scientific and technological
discoveries, but I I think many people
when they start to think about how AI is
transforming everyday life in in many
communities, I I I worry and I I think
that some of their earliest interactions
won't be with driverless cars. They'll
be with cameras that are tracking
license plates. And in many communities
around the country, I I read stories
about people who are chopping down AI
cameras from Flock or other companies
because they feel that somehow they're
being surveiled by their police
department. You read stories about
police departments federating their
surveillance data to enable new forms of
tracking. Uh on the the odd case, I I
think this is what Darth Vader was
gesturing at perhaps. uh you read
stories of police and other first
responders using their access to these
AI cameras to stalk uh ex partners. And
so I I I think flock in in some ways has
become the petri dish for uh either
surveillance or what um you know an old
friend Dave Brin might call surveillance
of who gets to see whom inside the
panopticon that AI enables. In China,
it's pretty obvious that the party gets
to look through the cameras at everyone
else. In the US, we're we're grappling
with this right now. If we put smart
cameras everywhere that can look at
every public space and then they're all
federated, so you can track movements of
cars, who gets to look at the data? And
I So, I think Darth Vader testifying
before the the city of San Diego. I
think this is like a very American
moment when we have the Empire
testifying on behalf of surveillance and
not surveillance.
Salem, you and I have, you know, talked
about the loss of privacy a lot. Uh, and
you know, the fact that people assume
they have privacy, they want privacy,
but I think that's pretty much a myth at
this point. What are your thoughts on
flock?
>> I have a lot of thoughts here and I
think this is a very, very dangerous
moment. Um, I've gone to see a bunch of
rock rush concerts lately, but let me
quote Pink Floyd here. This is another
brick in the wall,
>> right? This is a huge that's Pink Floyd
flipping over to show some level of
thing. But there's a huge structural
pattern because now we've transitioned
from find this suspect to find me people
who behave like suspects and that's a
very very different animal. Pattern
matching now becomes essentially free
meaning surveillance stops being
constrained by manpower at all. Right?
And so civil liberties were were kind of
protected to some level by the friction
because following everybody was just too
expensive. And now that's gone. The cost
of following everybody has gone to zero.
So this is a big uh structural problem
in terms of you already have cases where
uh police officers are using this
technology to track their partners uh to
track for ex-girlfriends and
ex-boyfriends and stuff. Um, you've
already had people literally dying
because they were banned for they got
tagged with the wrong license plates
because the flock read it wrong. This is
a massive issue with completely wipes
out our civil liberties in some ways.
And you got to be really careful as to
how and the problem is technologies
eliminated the cost of mass surveillance
now. Okay. And the constitution does not
update when transaction costs go to
zero. This is a very very big moment. I
think I like the way Alex frames it.
This puts this whole thing in a petri
dish to bring up to this level of
conversation. We need to have this kind
of conversation at a constitutional
level to say how do we want to be how do
we want to operate in this environment.
Now we are very close now to essentially
where the Chinese have CCP mandating it
and they just operate that way because
that's what it is. But essentially we're
in the same place here. It's just done
by corporations and by unwarranted uh um
fairly rogue police forces and
surveillance systems. So it's a very
very delicate moment. I don't think it
ends well.
>> Uh you know I want to just strongman
this a moment. You know this is not just
CCP. This is also uh the Emirates for
example. I was just having conversation
with with Jamie Justice who heads our
our life sciences at X-Prise. And she
was saying she went out for a run. She's
a prolific runner. Oh my god. getting up
at like 6:00 a.m., but she went out for
a run at like 10 p.m. at night in the
streets of Dubai and she felt she would
never do that in the US and she felt
completely safe. I mean, so you're
trading some level of civil liberties,
you know, I there's always a trade like
when you go through uh you know, customs
at the airport and you're no longer
waiting in giant lines because you know,
facial detection puts you through
instantly. Uh I'll make that trade. I
will happily make that trade to save
myself time and I'll make the trade as
well on increased safety for my kids. So
the question is do we put this at an
individual vote or is this society
saying we we you know value safety over
privacy?
>> I just have to remind of the the Ben
Franklin quote they who can give up
essential liberty to obtain a little
temporary safety deserve neither liberty
nor safety.
>> Yes. Yes, I'm with you. This is this is
very very dangerous. I have I have a I
have I have a personal experience here.
I once came into the US and they took me
aside and said, "Sorry, you have to miss
your flight because um there's an Afghan
warlord by the name Sully Mismile wanted
by the FBI for poppy trading." And I'm
like, "What?" And they're like, "We have
good news and bad news." I'm like,
"Okay, good news, you're you know, Vice
President Yahoo. It's pretty clear. You
speak at all these conferences. We're
pretty clear you're not an Afghan
warlord." I'm like, "Ph, glad to hear
that. What's the bad news?" The bad news
is we're not allowed to make that
judgment call. We have to check the
Washington. It'll take a few hours. Have
a seat.
>> Don't you wish
you wish?
>> Yeah. And it took like it took like a
few years to get that cleared up. And so
I said to them, "Does that mean every
sel gets stopped like this?" And they
said, "Sir, you have no idea when Juan
Rodriguez commits a misdemeanor, it
means we have to take aside every Juan
Rodriguez." [laughter] And this is where
you could get the benefits of test
technology because it can disamiguate
and names resolve at the name level very
quickly with technology. On the bad
side, the negative consequences and
accidental consequences like innocent
until proven guilty habius corpus is
essentially gone now in the US. This is
a really really bad place. So I don't
know how this resolves. Uh but I think
the Ben Finequin quote should be sitting
on the front desk tattooed in front of
everybody for the next 10 years to solve
this. It's a very big problem
>> as an Afghan warlord from now on the
[laughter]
>> you can't you can't alleged alleged
alleged Afghan warlord nothing was ever
proven. Uh [laughter] but this this is a
real this is a real problem. And you
know I got to a point and I have to say
something. The folks that I've ever
encountered at the US uh immigration
border have never ever been anything
short of beautifully professional and
constructive. That's been my experience.
Like unbelievably proper, appropriate,
etc. Um but for a few times I'm like uh
guys they're like, "Yeah, we know you're
not the Afghan ruler, but have a seat.
We got to check. We we just have to go
through this process."
>> Might have shaved your hair. [laughter]
>> Yeah. It got to a point where I was
almost on a firstname basis as some of
the immigration folks that are just
traveling so much and they're like, "Oh,
Mr. Ismail, have a seat. We have to do
an identity check." Having gone through
the same border 15 times, they they know
me, etc. But this is one of the issues
that we have to resolve and it causes
massive problems. If you get caught on
the wrong side of that,
>> it can go very badly for quite a while.
We resolve it, right? Can try and fix
the systems, etc. It's a really, really
difficult problem. And we can use
technology in very powerful constructive
ways, but we really risk losing a lot of
civil liberties here cuz especially if
you have an a an environment or a
government that's not friendly towards
you in the in the UAE, they have a
benevolent dictatorship, right? And as
long as it stays benevolent and they're
about as benevolent as you could
possibly imagine there, that why that's
why there's so much incredible safety.
Nobody the minute you step out of line
they they take you out very quickly and
therefore everybody feels incredibly
safe and it's a fabulous thing but the
problem with benevolent dictatorships is
they typically don't stay benevolent
very long uh and that's a structural
problem right the solution
>> we have to really figure out
>> sorry we have one we have to figure out
human governance now at a level that
we've never had to deal with before this
is for me one of the singularities right
how do you uh construct
regulatory frameworks can have any hope
of keeping up with the pace of
technology.
>> Sorry, Alex. What one of the solutions
that has been proposed, I know David
Brin and and others have advocated for
this is give everyone access to these
surveillance capabilities. Allow the
civilians to to do the same license
plate tracking that first responders and
police have. Let everyone track
everyone. If it's a public space, make
it a public resource.
>> That's right. And and I'm a huge fan of
EFF and the work that they do there.
They've highlighted some of these
things. For example, in Russia, which is
a bit of a wild west, where a policeman
will come and break your headlight and
then give you a ticket and extract
corrupt bribes from you. The the
Russians were the first to adopt
dashboard cameras. Do you remember that
meteorite that hit in a decade ago? And
there was like 200 live videos of this
meteorite getting hit. So, somebody
asked the question, why the hell how the
hell do we have 200? How many people had
live time to whip out their cell phone
cameras and track this thing real time?
It wasn't that. It's just that the
Russians have learned they better have a
dashboard camera to prevent against uh
police uh dodgy police extortion.
So, they all have dashboard cameras to
to for for their own safety. Uh and that
tracked all those those things. So that
you can see in that case the citizenry
is starting to point the camera the
other way and we need a ton more of that
and I think Alex's point is really
important. Everybody should have access
to these systems so that you can see
what's going on.
>> Amazing. All right, let me move us along
here. Some fun news on the uh on my
personal front or my ex-priseze front.
So, as you guys may know, we put out a
call for optimistic, hopeful visions of
the future. Uh, this is the Future of
Vision X-P Prize. We had over 5,000
teams registered. Uh, 2,550
video trailer submissions. It was
amazing. It blew us away. Largest film
competition ever. And we're down to the
final 50. And we're asking for you to
help us vote. So, uh, you can go to my
tweet on this at Peter Dmandis, my
X-prise handle, or you can go to this
link down below, uh,
vote.futurevisionexprize.com,
and you'll be served up two videos at a
time, and the question is, which future
do you prefer? You vote on one, then
you'll be served up the next two, and
we're doing essentially an ELO bubble
sort here. Uh, and we're going to be
bringing the top five of these uh, to
the Moonshots Live uh, summit here. So,
uh, just a quick reminder, guys, on
September the 25th, uh, you're going to
have a chance to meet all the Moonshot
mates. Alex, Emod, Dave, and Sele will
all be there. Uh, and we'll be doing a,
uh, Moonshot's live, uh, broadcast from
there. Uh, and we have incredible
speakers. Uh, we're going to have Palmer
Lucky is going to be there talking
about, you know, his entrepreneurial
journey. Our mission there is help you,
you know, discover your purpose,
discover your moonshot. Uh we're going
to have Astroteller there helping you
shape your moonshot. Uh how do you build
a moonshot organization? Ben Lamb, the
creator of Colossal, which has gone from
0 to10 billion valuation for years. Uh
Kathy Wood, Neil Degrass Tyson, Neil
Stevenson, an incredible author. Uh
gentlemen, uh what? So let's go each of
you. So See, what are you going to be
talking about at Moonshots? Uh I'll be
talking about my normal stuff which is
how does humanity cope with all of this
but specifically I'll be talking about
the organizational singularity and how
do you when a world is changing this
fast how do you build organizational
structures that are resilient for this
new world but I but I cannot wait to
interact with all the other folks and
you know I think of this thing as AI is
great in the virtual we're great in the
virtual as a podcast but we're much more
fun in the physical where where we can
kind gauge and kind of check each other
out. I can't wait to meet a lot of our
fans. Um, I've had so many comments from
people. My whole community wants to
come. So, we've got a whole issue around
how do we get tickets and allocate that.
It's going to be one of the funnest days
ever. I can't wait for this. Uh, I think
we may have to do something like this
quarterly, by the way, just to keep
>> Oh my god, I love this. Or daily or real
time as Alex would talk about. Just get
in one big room and and hell with
everything else.
>> Yeah, this is live. Live.
>> Yes,
>> live. 247. And Alex, you're going to be
on uh we have, by the way, through the
day an incredible program with uh with
the mates and then the evening uh each
of the mates is going to be spending an
hour with you. So, Alex, what are you
going to be doing uh during your hour
with all our guests?
>> Well, I think the question is what are
the questions?
>> I think the agenda calls for an AMA. So,
I'm extremely curious to hear what the
questions are and uh do my best to
dispel any myths that I might be
biological.
[laughter]
>> And Dave, you're going to be doing a
deep dive in AI investing. Talk more,
please.
>> Well, I'm anticipating we're moving into
this red pill, blue pill world where you
can choose to be oblivious to all of
this and be happy living it out without
being aware of it, or you can choose to
be in the middle of it. I'm anticipating
every attendee of this event has decided
to take the red pill and be in the
middle of it. And so then they're going
to be asking, okay, what do I do
career-wise? What do I invest in? What
are the scarce constraints of the
future? You know, what how do I interact
with these 11 magnum mobstick companies?
You know, are they going to crush me or
are they going to be my friend? All of
those questions are going to come up
with this gang. And I want to be
prepared to answer every single one of
of those lifeanging I have a spe I have
a specific question I want to ask Neil
Stevenson.
>> Yeah.
>> Which is, you know, if you went back 10
20 years and he's writing doing all
these amazing novels, uh, you had some
sense of what a glimmer of what the
future might hold, right? In a world
that we live in today where it's so hard
to predict where things are going in 3
months, forget 3 years or 30 years, how
do you build the models that give you
viable future narratives? And that's the
question I've got for you.
>> You know, I spent the day with Neil
Stevenson, one of the most extraordinary
science fiction writers, right? He wrote
Diamond Age, Young Ladies, illustrator,
Primmer over Snow Crash. Wow.
>> Snow Crash, Seven Eaves. He wrote that
over 30 years ago, and I just reread it
and it's perfect. I mean, it's so good.
>> It's so good. It is held over 30 years,
>> right? Predict going. Yeah. It's it's
>> Yeah, because you know we should ask him
to be a guest, Peter, because it would
be really great to get his,
>> you know, he's not he's brilliant. He's
not really a live stage kind of guy, but
I'd love to have him a guest. If anyone
could open him up on a on a live
environment, it would be us. That would
be fantastic. You know, one of his other
themes that I think is incredibly
relevant over 30 years is if if you look
at the world leaders today, they're
overwhelmingly really, really old. And
if you survey young people and say, 'D
do you aspire to be president someday?
No. Absolutely positively not. And so
like, okay, in Neil's books, society
worldwide cuts the other direction. It's
not like I'm in this country. I'm
trapped in this country. I live in this
country. People actually in the age of
AI cut in the other direction where
people all over the world are
like-minded on a topic and they bond
through global communication, through
Starlink and through AI across
countries, which could be a great sign
for for future global peace. So, I'd
love to talk to Neil about that.
>> We're also going to have Rod Rodenberry
there, the the son of Gene Rodenberry.
Star Trek is an underlying theme at
Moonshots Live 2026. Yeah, Alex,
>> I I think in some ways, ju just on the
sci-fi note and Neil Stevenson, I I
think in some ways it was easier,
ironically, 30 years ago to write sci-fi
that was predictive than it was in the
decade or two after that. that Peter
Teal and others have made the point or
suggested that the 90s might have been a
local optimum in terms of clarity on the
future because we had the economy
booming, we had the dotcom boom, we had
the internet hitting consumers and so if
if you imagine that history isn't sort
of a monotonic exponential or at least
consumer and broad populist perception
of the history isn't like a smooth
exponential but es and flows and has
booms and busts then a moment of peak
clarity would come during a boom. when
you're able to sort of see above the
tree line and see where we're going. And
then when you're in a local bust, you
you lose the forest for the trees and
you lose clarity. So by that metric that
would also have I I think the the happy
side effect of explaining why golden age
science fiction from call it the the 50s
or so postworld war II era sci-fi was
also a local moment of clarity when you
could see rockets and you could see
vision based energy too cheap to meter
and and so by by that metric then I
would say it's not that surprising that
so much amazing sci-fi was written in
the '90s from Neil from Charlie St from
others
>> Robert Heinline. Yeah.
>> Yes. Amazing. Uh so everybody, we've got
200 seats left. This is an event of 1500
people, uh creators and builders,
entrepreneurs. It's going to be a power
networking event for you to meet your
next co-founder, for you to meet
investors. Uh so join us. You can go to
moonshots.com to apply. Uh I expect
we're going to be closing out all the
seats in the next two weeks. So don't
delay. Join us for the inaugural
Moonshots live event. It's uh all day on
the 25th of September. uh starts
registration starts at 7:00. At 8:00 you
have a chance to have photos with all
the Moonshot mates. Uh then we go into
the program from 9:00 a.m. till 6 and
then there's a party that evening and an
incredible unconference. And we have a
super special event. I can't announce it
yet. It's it's I'm so excited about this
the evening before the evening of
Thursday the 24th. I'll let you know as
soon as I can, but it's incredible. I
have one more quick thing to say about
this.
>> Um, you know, when we did our week-long
singularity executive programs, the
funnest session ever for everybody
universally was the unconference. Yeah.
>> Right. And for folks that don't know,
what you do is you put up a set of rooms
and a bit of a timeline. People get up
and say, "I'm going to talk about uh AI
and biotech." And they put up a thing
and they somebody else gets up and says,
"I'm going to talk about this." And they
put up a little poster. and you go
wherever you feel like going. Uh, and
it's turns out to be the most incredibly
engaging sessions you can ever have. And
so if you ever get a chance to
participate in an unconference, go do
it. But an unconference of this crowd
will be absolutely epic. This is
something I'm excited to meet all of our
so our our
>> listen because we've got you look at the
comments we have. We have some really
really smart um followers and
commentators. It'll be unbelievable.
Unbelievable.
It'll be amazing. Nice and swarm.
>> Yes, for sure.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, [music] autonomous software
development with infinite code context.
Blitzy uses thousands of specialized AI
agents that think for hours to
understand enterprise scale code bases
with millions of lines of code.
Engineers start every development sprint
with the Blitzy platform, bringing in
their development requirements. The
Blitzy platform provides a plan, then
generates and pre-ompiles code for each
task. Blitzy delivers 80% or more of the
development work autonomously while
providing a guide for the final 20% of
human development work required to
complete the sprint. Enterprises are
achieving a 5x engineering velocity
increase when incorporating Blitzy as
their preIDE development tool, pairing
it with their coding co-pilot of choice
to bring an AI native SDLC into their
org. Ready to 5x your engineering
velocity? Visit blitzy.com to schedule a
demo and start building with Blitzy
today. [music]
>> All right, moving us along. Uh we're
going to jump into the stories around
jobs. um actually have three stories
around jobs. The first story is an
article this week in the Washington Post
reported an analysis that predicted the
job apocalypse is unlikely to happen. So
again, I've been saying for a while this
has been really murky. You have half the
community out there saying we're going
to lose all the jobs. The other half
saying no, we have job growth. So the
Washington Post argues that historically
technology transitions from the loom to
the automobile to the internet
consistently created more jobs than they
destroyed. And we've had that
conversation on the pod here many times.
You know, it displaces specific tasks uh
rather than entire occupations while
creating new categories of work that
were never previously even conceived of.
The thesis of the Washington Post uh
article is AI is not replacing jobs. It
is replacing tasks within jobs and the
people who learn to use AI become more
productive not less employed. So that's
the first story. Let me go on to the
second one. Uh and we'll stop there and
then then sele I know you have a
particular story you're going to cover
here. So the second the second story uh
comes out of Goldman Sachs which this
week warned that professional services
firms consulting law accounting face an
existential risk as AI capabilities
improve faster than their partners can
adapt creating a dangerous skill gap
where junior staff trained on AI
outperform senior partners who refuse to
use it. The skills gap is not between
the educated uneducated. It between the
AI fluent and the AI resistant and the
AI fluent are increasingly the juniors
and not the partners. So uh Selma I'm
going to go to you first and you can
call for your slide whenever you want as
well.
>> Yeah. Two or three things. First you
know let's all uh and urge everybody you
know to please be evidentiary and
datadriven in your orientation for how
you view the world, right? Um there are
people that doomsday Bill Gates
yesterday was it that came out and said
oh my god all the jobs two days ago
>> two days ago okay and let me just call
out here I'm a massive fan of Bill Gates
and his philanthropy but as a futurist
somewhat of a dismal track record he
missed the internet he missed mobile and
commenting about the future of work I
don't think is the right thing to do in
area like this um the and by the way
this is true of of I find of of Ray
Dalio or Larry Frink or um um um uh the
other folks that do commentation the
Pikid Yuval Harrari they tend to be
unbelievably great at framing the past
somewhat questionable on the future
right because many of the time they
don't really understand exponential
which is a whole thing and so you really
have to be careful around all of this if
you look at say the the uh Goldman Sachs
or the professional services firm uh
conversation deeply disagree why because
as the world gets more volatile
companies are going to need more help
than less because that volatility will
require a lot of help which is what
we're seeing. You'll have to change your
business model from selling hours to
selling outcomes which is starting to
happen but I don't think that's uh that
big of a deal. Um the the a bigger thing
I think is the jobs question and I would
love if we could throw up the slide
right here. Uh so um uh principal
financial group uh friend of the pod
they bunch of them watch us on a regular
basis uh did a survey and to give you a
sense principal financial group helps uh
small businesses with u health health
plan benefit plan retirement etc at the
small business level formemes they have
130,000
customers right this is a big big
company with a great cross-section
across the entire country and frankly
around the world. Uh here is what they
are seeing. They did a survey across a
very meaningful representative sample
here and what they found was uh only 4%
of the companies anticipate that AI will
reduce staffing and wages. 31%
expected this is small to mediumsiz
enterprises expect increase
>> which is the majority of the workforce
by the way
>> which is the majority of the workforce.
And let's note a very very um important
factoid. Over the last 50 60 years, 100%
of job growth has come from small to
mediumsiz companies. Big companies
getting bigger but also getting more
efficient. Net value job creation zero.
100% job growth has come from small to
mediumsiz companies. So this is the
demographic to track if you're
interested in the future of work. And
31% expect increasing staffing and
increasing wages, right? um 10% uh say
they don't use AI. Uh last year it was
19% and now it's down to 10%. Okay. Um
uh of the people that have reduced staff
only 1.4%
attributed those to AI or automation.
Okay. This is so inverse.
>> This is so fantastic.
>> It's so inverted to the current
BS tropes of radical unemployment that
we see there. It's unbelievable. So,
please people look at the data, right?
Look at this uh uh stuff. We can get you
the full report if you're interested. Uh
and look at the staffing trends just in
the last few months. 52% have increased
staff, 30% have maintained it, and only
12% over the last 3 months of reduced
staff. So, this is very, very recent and
a great projector of where things are
going. It's completely opposite to the
the oh my god, jobs are everything is
going to take all the jobs. And this is
where to track the future in actual
reality.
>> Love it. A great optimism story. Uh Dave
or Alex, you want to jump in?
>> Uh I think we've come full circle
actually in in the sense that remember
when we were talking to Elon, you know,
he was predicting great social unrest
with unprecedented abundance going on
concurrently.
>> Yes.
>> And and what the labs have now decided
is well look, if I if I automate
everybody's job and they're all
unemployed, I need to give them a new
sense of purpose. What's their new sense
of purpose? Well, that job I used to
have gave me a sense of purpose.
[laughter]
like why did we take it away in the
first place? So now what they're doing
is saying look we don't need to displace
everybody's job just for the sake of
automating everything. We're going to
leave everybody alone while we work on
incredible new breakthroughs and and we
have infinite soldout tokens anyway. So
we don't need to disrupt all these
voters and and so that's the way it's
going to play out. But I'll tell you,
when I was a kid, we were the first
people that we knew to get a PC, an
Apple 2.
>> Mh.
>> And begged and pleaded, my brother and I
begged and pleaded our parents to get
this this Apple 2. And it was
life-changing for me. But I I showed my
dad like, "Hey, there's a word processor
called Superscribe, and you don't have
to be handwriting all your notes
anymore." He was like, "You know what?
I'm I'm in my 40s. I've been doing it
this way my whole life. I don't need to
be a computer person." And so he
finished out his entire career at GE not
being a computer person like huh this
and I can kind of forgive him for that
because the the you know the PCs would
break all the time. The printer was a
nightmare like okay it was hard. This is
not hard to do relatively speaking and
it rewards builders and creators and
visionaries regardless of their
technical skills. You you you are
absolutely empowered by this. So you're
crazy not to get on the bandwagon, but
AI is going to allow you to not do it.
You know, we're actually making the door
open to not get on the bandwagon. I get
the question a lot, okay, as AI is
automating lots of stuff, what will
human be human beings be doing, right?
And the best kind of metaphor I've come
up with is if you went back a 100 years
and you're looking at accounting, people
are doing double entry bookkeeping in
big ledgers, credit over here, debit
over there in pencil with a big eraser
and a whole set of uh tabular columns
and lots of ledgers. uh as we moved to
automation, we had calculators and slide
rules that help you do the tabulation
faster, but we're still doing the t
entries by hand. Today, we have
accounting software that does read your
bank account, does all the entries
automatically, okay? And the human being
has lifted above the loop, not in the
loop. The human being is above the loop
and is categorizing the transactions
looking for problems categorizing
vendors and types of income coming in
figuring out reconciliation gaps looking
at the loop process flows and it's much
more value added to be there than doing
the rote double entry whatever this is
what we see happening Eric Brunson calls
this white collar drudgery there's a
huge amount of stuff happening in big
companies it's a lot of massaging of
information taking stuff from this sales
report putting it over here etc etc and
all of that will be taken out where you
can do really curatorial judgment
thinking work and and applying
experience to it rather than doing the
actual work itself and people miss that
and I'll go back to my specific
experience writing the first book was
three years of hell just horrible
because you had no help sec [laughter]
>> well no the the first book I was partly
with you but but it was just you had to
write every line and check every line
yourself etc right second book Peter
that you and it together fully. Um, it
was 2 and 1/2 years, but even more hell
because you kept having to think how
much of the first book do you bring
over, etc., etc. And by the way, it was
an absolute joy working with you. So,
don't you dare say anything like that.
And the third part, but this third book
has been 6 months of unadulterated joy
because I can say, "Oh, um, Bill Gates
just said this or Satya Nadella said
this. Look through the book. Tell me as
a developmental editor where we should
put inserts, etc. Scan the things." And
it's absolute pure fun. And people
forget how much more fun it is when
something's doing all of that cognitive
uh BS stuff that everybody had to think
about. And now you can do pure uh
thinking judgment. You can be much much
more creative. And this is the heart of
what it comes down to. It all of this
automation and AI enablement and
cognitive abundance allows us to be
deeply deeply deeply creative. And that
is the most fulfilling place you can be
as a human being.
>> Beautifully said. Let me let me hop on
Dave on Dave on your point. Uh, and I'm
sure everybody listening here at the pod
is using AI and uh and uh enjoying these
conversations, but if you have someone
in your life who isn't, I I think the
most important thing to realize is you
have access to the most patient, most
capable teacher on the planet, right?
Pick your favorite model and ask it just
to begin at zero. You know, I don't
understand this. I just heard this term.
help me, you know, create a curriculum
for me to go from not understanding AI
to fundamentally being able to use it.
And I think at a minimum, spend 30
minutes a day in conversation with your
favorite model. Um, it's that easy. It's
free. It's everywhere on your phone.
There's no reason not to dive in. You
know, there's, you know, human
cognitive, uh, you know, uh, challenges
typically prevent a person from jumping
to something they don't understand. But
it is never been easier in the world.
Um, Alex or Dave, do you want to close
us out on this one?
>> Yeah, I'll just comment. I I think the
original impetus for the story was
actually from friend of the pot Eric
Brinson, as you mentioned, Sem. I I
think there are many people in this
economy who don't realize that not only
do they have permission to be high
agency, but we're now in a regime where
high agency and agency in general is one
of the few human traits that is actively
rewarded in an era of super
intelligence. People think agency is
something I I suspect, this is my my
theory of the case. I think too much of
the human economy, at least in the
American economy, the one I'm most
familiar with, think agency is something
exhibited by superheroes in movies in
Hollywood and don't realize that the
shackles are off. Anyone can exhibit
high agency empowered by super
intelligence now, not just in the
cinema. And that to the contrary, this
is one of the few things left that can
actually yield extreme vertical
mobility. So if you're listening and
you're not, you know, to to Dave's
point, you're not fully availing
yourself of super intelligence to
accomplish superhuman feats, I encourage
you to start now because I think there's
a window of time and I don't know how
long it's going to last. Maybe only a
handful of years. Do it now. Otherwise,
do it never.
>> Yeah. Wow. I want you to reflect on
that. Society will reward agency in this
world of AI automation. That's such a
great point because the more you are a
self-starter and have the gumption to go
ahead and do this and build something
with it, the more that you'll be
rewarded. Absolutely love it.
>> Alex Alex said extreme upward mobility.
We'll use that as a theme at the
Moonshot Summit, but the data behind
what he just said is it's like nothing
you've ever seen before. like the gap is
getting wider and wider but the the rate
of upward mobility that's possible has
never been seen before.
>> How's it possible to be depressed if you
anybody watches this is my question.
>> Yeah, I mean it's such an amazing time
and I love your story. Thank you for
sharing that data. It's a it's data.
It's data driven optimism is what it is
for
>> that. Do you mean that or the Afghan
warlord thing? [laughter]
>> You mean this one? Okay.
>> All right.
>> You too can be an Afghan warlord.
Everyone can be an Afghan warlord.
[laughter]
There's agency of a different kind.
There's hope for everyone.
>> Let's jump into the world of data
centers, chips, and compute. Uh two
breaking stories uh this week. Uh the
first comes out of the global affairs
team at X. Let me share a slide and then
we'll talk about this. What does it
mean? Um and uh and you know, is this
data absolutely 100%. So this is what
was posted on X uh by the global affairs
team at X. It says, quote, "The ex
safety team conducted an investigation
into suspected Chinese inauthentic
accounts involved in influence
operations.
We identified a bot farm of
approximately 200,000 accounts. Within
this farm, we found 200 accounts posting
in a manner that could manipulate a
legitimate debate about American AI and
energy policy. These posts contained
claims that AI data centers are driving
up household electricity prices and
straining the grid. Others include AI
generated cartoons that depicted data
center operations enriching them
operators enriching themselves at the
public expense. And here we're showing
one of those cartoons. Uh and you know
we've talked about this. You know what's
causing this 75%
you know not in my backyard sentiment.
you know, where people would rather have
a nuclear power plant in their backyard
than a data center. It seems completely
illogical. Um, the second story is one I
want to put front and center. It comes
out of Quincy, Washington, where the
data centers have had extraordinary
positive civic impact. This story
reported on CNN says, "Data centers
helped resurrect Quincy, Washington,
where the poverty rate fell from 29.4%
to 6.2%.
tech tax revenue funded a new high
school, hospital, library, police and
fire stations while residents property
taxes their rates decreased. This is a
story about the tech industry uh
succeeding and and and bluntly this is
the story that the tech industry needs
to be telling and needs to be making
happen. So uh gentlemen, your thoughts
on this?
>> Shocked. Shocked I say that there are
foreign influence operations attempting
to suppress American AI data center
deployment. Shocked
>> Selene or Dave
>> standard SCOPS you you'd expect to see
this happen. The the difficult part is
we have really no easy defense against
it. And the problem I say and I
mentioned this a couple of podcasts ago
is that the people in the US are very
very narrative driven rather than
evidence- driven. That's the problem.
Um, I mean, I don't know what the US is
doing in China, but you know, it's the
numbers here, the numbers here are
crazy, right? So, we'll we'll we've
talked about this before. Uh, if if you
or someone you know is against data
centers, please dig and look at the
numbers. Water is not an issue. energy,
these data centers. You know, the right
policy is is the county says, "Okay, you
can build here, but generate your own
power or subsidize, you know, community
power so it's cheaper." And for God's
sakes, to the hyperscalers, invest in
the schools, invest in the libraries. I
don't libraries are this anymore, but in
invest in the community. That's the
right way to do it. Take a fraction of
the cost and make everybody's life there
better.
>> But Peter, you're you're gesturing at I
think something interesting. libraries.
The libraries remember the digital
divide and concerns that some areas
might be left behind with less compute.
And now we're seeing whether as a result
of foreign influence ops or or other
political factors, the exact opposite
where all of these regions that could in
principle be economically uplifted and
energetically uplifted and compute
uplifted are worried their hand ringing
that they might be suffering from too
much compute. How much the tide has
turned.
>> Amazing. Well, every now and then
there's a story where we just absolutely
positively need to get to the truth and
you know that we saw this during that co
outbreak where it's like look this is
this is a medical thing. What's the
actual truth do the masks work? Does I
mechan work? You know we need absolute
truth and instead we got politics. You
know we got an a Republican opinion and
a Democrat opinion and then now Fouch's
on trial. Like come on man this is
We need the absolute truth on
this story. Like are the Chinese is it
the policy of the CCP to disrupt
American opinion on data centers, slow
down our construction of AI, bypass us
in AI, and then control the world by
winning the race to RSI? Is that their
plan? Or if you talk to Alvin Gralin,
he's like they don't even think vaguely
that way. They're just trying to have a
better life for themselves and improve
their own progress. They don't could
care less about trying to invade the US
with with false stories. Which is the
true story? I don't actually know. But
we absolutely don't. We don't need
politics on this. We need to know what
is actually going on.
>> Well, what what's actually going on is
data centers are not the enemy.
>> They're an economic engine that can
revive a community
>> uh that's been left behind. I mean,
that's the reality. I you know, it's
like please come here.
>> Yeah. Dave, didn't so there's no doubt
that you're right about that, Peter.
Data centers are one of the best things
we can pos they are the best thing we
can possibly be doing right now. 100%
true. And if the CCP loses that battle,
they'll move on to some societal AI like
it's it's corrupting your children, stop
building it or something like that. So
we we need to know they will they'll
keep coming back with false story after
false story if that's their policy and
it's we're so vulnerable to it. So I
just like they'll they'll hypothetically
maybe come up with some sort of
infinitely scrollable streaming video
app that that will become insanely
popular on mobile phones and
>> addictive to all the kids.
>> Just speaking hypothetically
>> I I think American companies are doing a
great job at that already. Um but that's
a different story. All right, let's
let's let's move on. So, OpenAI released
the first new performances of their chip
Jalapeno. Uh, it's a custom inference
chip developed with Broadcom. Uh,
reporting 1.5 to 1.9x more AI work per
watt and up to 3.6x lower endtoend
latency as compared to Nvidia's GB200s
and GB300's. Halleluino runs on 700
watts uh against the GB300 that runs at
1400 watts, half the power, 1.5 times
the peak power uh token rate per
kilowatt. Uh performance here uh you
know the significance here is that
OpenAI is not is no longer just a
customer of Nvidia. They're becoming a
chip designer. And I I saw a great
interview where Jensen was being asked
by the reporter, you know, how do you
feel about your largest customer
competing with you now? So I I think
this is what we're going to see
everybody doing. Everybody's moving up
and down the stack. They want
independence.
>> Yeah, there's no doubt inference is
moving off of Nvidia for sure. And you
know the 100x performance gain, this is
the first 2x of 100x performance gains.
That does not mean Nvidia has a problem
though because training is staying on
Nvidia and training is infinitely sold
out just like inferences. But there's an
enormous you know 90% of the compute is
inference time. So there's an enormous
new industry for inference only
emerging. The other side of the story is
that, you know, this was just an idea at
OpenAI just a few months ago and now
it's a production chip. So, so that
shows you how short the cycle time on
innovation is becoming with AI
assistance.
>> Yeah, Alex,
>> a few thoughts on this. Maybe the most
startling statistic that OpenAI put out
regarding Jalapeno was the throughput
per second per user. So tokens per
second per user increase that they got
on Jalapeno not just on their frontier
models but on their open source models
like you remember GPTO OSS they got they
claim almost a 54x throughput increase
hosting GPTOSS
versus what they obliquely refer to I
guess as their as the existing best
presumably a reference to some NVIDIA
architecture that's so startling uh open
PN And where is Broadcom in this?
Because obviously the only way that
OpenAI and and it was public information
that they worked with Broadcom on this,
but presumably the only way OpenAI using
their own AI to achieve a tape out so
quickly is in conjunction with a
Broadcom closed PN. This is so startling
and potentially such a huge throughput
increase. It makes me scratch my head
and wonder whether Open AI, remember how
we've talked in past about those who
can't compete compute, whether OpenAI
might actually do this to themselves,
even though they are competitive with
Anthropic. They're one of the the two
top tier frontier firms left. whether
they might actually choose to become a
hyperscaler themselves with their own
chips inhouse. I it's like crazy future
would be a heck of a plot twist. But I I
this has me wondering if if they have
such amazing balance of prefill of the
prompt uh with uh me otherwise memory
bandwidth uh limited decoding for LLMs
whether OpenAI wants the optionality in
a year or two of saying hey market in
addition to our own models we're going
to we're going to respond to the
competitive threat of Chinese openweight
models and other openweight models by
surprise. Open AAI offers its own cloud.
We'll call it OpenAI compute. It'll be
hosted on OpenAI chips and we'll still
make money just like Elon is. He's he's
making money handoverfist hosting
everyone else's models including
anthropic. I I think we're in such a
crazy future where I could imagine a
world where say an open AI compute cloud
hosts an anthropic model and OpenAI and
Anthropic win at the same time.
>> Love it.
>> I have a Wow. Okay. I have a question
for you guys.
>> Yeah.
>> One of the things that was mentioned was
that the the Nvidia's CUDA uh moat may
be dead in this next few coming years.
How big of a deal is that? Because CUDA
seem to be their moat, right?
>> Yeah. Know Cuda. So it just it's
important to be clear like CUDA is still
the dominant mode for AI researchers who
are working on new training.
>> Take a second and explain what CUDA is
for those who don't know.
>> Yeah. So kuda. So all the all the AI
researchers in the world move to Python
and PyTorch to do the because you can
iterate your ideas so much more quickly
in that environment and then to run it
at scale you're like well here's my code
just run. The only way to say just run
is the CUDA layer translates your
PyTorch right into Nvidia micro kernels
runs at blazing fast speeds. uh Nvidia
invested a lot of time, human time,
coding that up, pre-AI coding and it
became so pervasive that when AI took
off, only Nvidia chips could be used for
all this training and research because
it it would have been a nightmare to try
and port all these mantle algorithms to
AMD or to some other vendor. And so
that's that's why Nvidia is the most
powerful company in the world or most
valuable company in the world today is
specifically because of that brilliant
early support of AI researchers when
nobody else cared about them. Uh so now
everyone's like well but now I can vibe
code anything in like a microscond. Why
is the CUDA thing still a moat? And at
inference time it's not. You know your
inference algorithms are so easy to port
to AMD or Intel that you you just you
don't care about CUDA. you can vibe up
your own solution. But for the advanced
researchers, they still overwhelmingly
use CUDA. Uh and and then you know,
Nvidia realized that CUDA can't last
forever. So they went and bought Melanox
to create massive high-speed
interconnect. So now their big moat is
look, if you want to run a 100,000 or a
million GPUs in one coherent cluster,
you still got to go with Nvidia only. So
I think Jensen's smart enough to know
that like your moat is only good until
the next moat. And so he's moving the
moat very intelligently and and he has a
huge amount of capital to keep moving
with it. But CUDA as the inference time
mode is already dead. CUDA as the
training time mode is probably limited
lifespan. But that's okay because the
interconnect is the new mode.
>> All right, let's turn to Apple. So,
Apple's new Mac Studio pairs the M5
Ultra with up to 512 GB of unified
memory, giving a desktop Mac enough
memory to run some of the largest open
AI models available locally on your
desktop. Apple unveiled also the M6, its
first chip manufactured at the 2nmter
process. So, finally, Apple is in the AI
game now pushing local AI as an
alternative to AI in the cloud. Uh,
Seem, you wanted to talk about this one.
your thoughts?
>> Well, just such an easy and obvious
thing for Apple to do, right? You would
have been they would if they hadn't done
this, they would have been the stupidest
company in history and they're not that
dumb. Uh the UN five 512 gig unified
memory puts a massive amount of
intelligence under your desk. So, this
really changes the economics from paying
per token perpetually to buying a
capital asset and then using it
continuously, right? especially that
Apple's gone to the extra level of
starting to lease its equipment out to
people. So, this is really a big deal. I
think the big winners here are comp law
firms, healthcare companies that have
HIPPA issues and can't put their stuff
on the cloud. Everything can much more
stuff can now be doing done on prem. And
I think this is going to be a for
medium-siz healthcare firms that can't
afford a private cloud and and doing all
that really really a big deal. And I
think this is a such a natural advantage
for Apple to go down this path. So you
get the four of these Mac studios
clustered together. Now you've got like
a small private data center. Like that's
a pretty big deal. Even Dave would go
full out for that
>> rather than
agents. [laughter]
>> I mean I look I'm at the end of my rope
with Apple. I mean like
>> I nobody has changed my life more that
I've never met than Steve Jobs. And the
Apple 2 that I got when I was a kid
totally changed my life. And then when
they came out with Mac OS based on
Linux, changed my life again. It's it's
absolutely the greatest company I've
ever seen. But they have totally missed
the boat. And it's just embarrassing
that a company with that much cash flow
has no AI strategy. Like they they don't
even deserve to be a Mag 7 company
anymore. It's just pathetic. So if the
best they can do in the age of AI is add
a bunch more RAM to a machine that they
already had, I mean, what the hell, man?
And I mean I I'm not saying this is a
great thing that they came out with, but
it's like 0.01% of what they should have
done by now in AI.
>> I total okay, I'm okay with all of that,
but but it's obvious they should have
done it. At least they did this, right?
>> The irony is the irony is even deeper.
So if if you look at the ancestry of how
unified memory architecture came about
and the the neural engine inside the M
series, you can trace the lineage back
to the Apple car. It was the Apple car
was the reason why Apple first
introduced the Apple car that never
happened. Why Apple introduced the
neural engine with access to this huge
unified memory addressable space. So I I
almost think like Apple's interaction
with AI is almost a history of hardware
that's too good for the software and or
conversely software that just isn't
worthy of the hardware. Apple had the
early unified
matmal acceleration built into a unified
addressing space. Apple had the TSMC
connection. Apple had the raw transistor
throughput to basically be Nvidia and
then some. And they fumbled it. They had
Siri before everyone else. They had
audio interaction. All of these various
forms and Apple software fumbled the
ball. And I can only hope that under
John Turnis that Apple is going to
decide it really does, you know, Tim
Cook used to always say and before Tim
Steve Jobs that they want it to be
hardware plus software plus services and
it just seems to me like Apple's
hardware at least to the consumer side
is incredible. Their services are also
not that bad, but they're so fumbling
and and so underutilizing still
infamously their amazing hardware with
their software. And [snorts] you know,
to to John, if if you're listening and
you're looking for guidance on what
Apple should be doing in this new era
under your C CEOship, please, please,
please just like take your amazing
hardware and unleash it with much better
software that integrates AI natively.
>> So, yes, hire Alex as a consultant first
and foremost. I don't need it.
[clears throat]
>> Well, well, do it. You'll do it because
you need it, not because Alex maybe for
charity. For charity. [laughter]
>> But also, the world needs it. Like Apple
is the one brand
>> that you can trust
>> with your information. It's the one and
only brand. And here we are in the age
of AI. Everyone's confused. It's
incredibly powerful. Like, it would
change the world.
>> Such a different world if Steve Jobs had
not made his stupid health decisions
and, you know, not treated his his
cancer. You know, Dave, I met I met
Steve once. I had a one-word
conversation with him.
>> So, I was having an ex-priseze an
ex-priseze meeting. Larry Paige, uh,
co-founder of Google, was on my board,
and he hosted us for an evening dinner.
And, uh, Loren Powell Jobs, his wife,
was there and and Steve was there in the
back of the room and we were talking
about the latest X-P prizes and the ones
that were just won. And, and afterward,
I had to go meet my hero over here. And
Steve is in the back of the room with
his arms folded the entire time like
this, looking kind of pissed off. And I
walked over, introduced myself, and I
said, "Steve, it's a real pleasure to
meet you." And he like, he like, you
know, barely nods his head. And then I
said, "You don't want to be here, do
you?" And he goes, "Nope." And that was
the entire conversation. [laughter]
>> I I've got a story. So, um, a couple of
months before the big, uh, iPhone
announcement in 2007, uh, Jerry Yang put
together a an offsite, a full day
offsite with all of Yahoo's vice
presidents. And Steve Jobs came in to do
a keynote, right? So, at a kind of a
handshake, hello. And Steve Jobs looks
at the audience and he goes, there were
like 300 people in the room, right? And
he's like, you have 300 vice presidents.
He's like, "I think I see the problem
with Yahoo right there." So, like the
fact that he had that much
organizational overhead, he was just
couldn't couldn't cope with that. My
claim to fame is I have a whole bunch of
MacBooks that were signed by Waznjak.
>> Oh, wow.
>> Cuz I I did a 90-minute debate with him
on stage a few years ago.
>> How old are you?
>> Yeah,
>> that one's about that was that's a few
years old. I had to I had to I had him
sign about four or five of them,
guarding them jealously.
>> Yeah. You got to preserve those in some
kind of
>> got to preserve got to preserve those.
Um and I gave a couple away to my
community cuz they were so thrilled with
that episode. It was a great
conversation. Steve Waznjak is famous
for coming out with all of this
technology gives us the opportunity to
do tinkering and just [clears throat]
playing around and that's the heart of
all creativity is just playing around
with technology to seeing what comes up
and he was really doubling down on that.
It was a great conversation, but that
that memory of Steve Jobs looking at 300
vice presidents going, I see, you think
I see what's wrong with your company has
never left me.
>> Oh my god.
>> It's funny. The very first share of
stock I ever bought was Apple. And I I
you know, we tend to overthink things.
Like all I had to do is just hold it.
[laughter]
>> I should still have that stock today.
>> I'm going to move us into the world of
abundance. Two stories on energy and one
on water. Uh again you know our mission
here is to deliver you datadriven
optimism why the world is getting
better. So uh let's hit energy first.
Again two stories here. The first story
uh is about uranium enrichment uh to
meet the growing needs of our advanced
gen 4 fision plants and the coming SMR
small modular reactor power plants. So
historically in the US conventional
reactor fuel in the form of uranium 238
has been enriched to about 3 to 5%. This
week, a commercial startup, again a
startup here, called Actonide said it
has demonstrated the ability to enrich
natural uranium into high assay
lowenriched uranium or halo up to a
purity of 15.38%
five times the traditional purity
previously achieved by you know all the
government labs. So a startup is
enriching uranium to this level and
that's for me a remarkable story. So,
every SMR company, and we had that
incredible podcast with Rome Nom on the
future of energy. If you haven't seen
it, please go see it. Every SMR company
says their reactors will be coming
online in 2030, but none of them have
the fuel and this could well be the
solution. Um, Alex, any thoughts on this
story?
>> Yeah, a number of thoughts. I I think
something went wrong right after World
War II. That's that's my best guess. In
the immediate aftermath of World War II,
so 80 years ago, the Atomic Energy
Commission was eventually formed in the
wake of the Manhattan Project. And I I
think something just got screwed up with
regard to how nuclear physics and
advanced physics in general was handled
in the postw World War II era. And the
government probably because of the bomb,
the the government granted itself under
the guise of mixed civilian military
leadership, the Atomic Energy
Commission. I think something
governance-wise got fumbled and I think
80 years on after the end of World War
II, we're finally starting to shake off
the quasi governmental monopoly on
nuclear physics. And I think I I suspect
there has been so much progress in an
alternative history, you know, sort of
for all mankind style where if in the
aftermath of World War II, if the Atomic
Energy Commission had either been
organized differently or we just had a
totally different governance structure
for advanced physics after the war, we
would have advanced so much more
quickly. And I I think startups like
Actonide that are producing Halo, I
think these are the tip of the iceberg
for all of the economic growth and
technological growth that can now be
unleashed now 80 years after World War
II. All of these shackles that we put on
our our own society perhaps with the
best of intentions are finally slowly
atrophying away. And just a a narrow
point on the technology here. So
>> please
>> this is nonobvious in many cases uranium
enrichment in this country to the extent
we do it at all and aren't just
importing enriched uranium from say
Russia uh the the technology that in
many cases is being used to enrich
uranium in this country is Manhattan
project level technology that has not
been materially improved since World War
II. It's using uranium hexafflloride gas
and centrifuges when we have much better
technology. There are alternative ways
to enrich uranium. For example, the uh
the term is a calatron. This was
technology that we've known in principle
how to make since the Manhattan project.
Rather than using centrifuges, spinning
uranium compound uh compounds in gaseous
form and then later having to compress
the gaseous uranium molecules down to
solid pellets or other solid forms that
could be used in reactors. We could
instead be using magnets,
electromagnetic magnetics and vacuum
systems and power electronics controls.
We have 80 years of advances in power
electronics that by and large are not
being used and have not been used to
enrich uranium either because we're
scared of doing it or because we've
handcuffed ourselves in terms of our
being able to do it. So I I I think I
think we should expect to see now that
the shackles are starting to come off in
a limited fashion from the postw World
War II era, we're going to start to see
80 years of chip advances and Moors law
advances finally being applied back to
this basically World War II era
technology and I think it'll create an
energy boom.
>> Well, I hope so. I think uh from a
venture capitalist point of view, you
would never in a million years have
invested in this when the regulatory
cost of getting a nuclear reactor up and
running is going to be a billion dollars
anyway. So you can see how the
dysfunction ripples through. You start
with government dysfunction and then the
venture capitalists are like well given
that that's dysfunctional I won't invest
in these innovations. So then the whole
value chain just doesn't go anywhere.
>> But now the SMR companies are being
funded by venture capitalists and they
are going public. Uh let's jump a little
bit about solar. Uh I'm going to show
this chart here. Uh this is a chart that
comes from Ember, the global energy
think tank. Uh they shared this data
showing China's increasing energy
generation both in solar and in nuclear.
So monthly solar generation in China has
exploded eightfold 800% over the past 6
years growing from 20 terowatts per
month in 2020 to about 160 terowatts per
month in mid 2026. At the same time,
nuclear power in China has increased by
at least 50% while the US nuclear uh
power gen has basically remained flat.
Uh need to remember that the AI race is
not just about chips. It's also about
the cost of energy to run those chips.
You know, the US is building its whole
data center power gen based on natural
gas, which is like six bucks per million
British thermal units, while China is is
basically getting this for near zero
marginal cost from uh from solar. And I
mean, I I think the abundant story here
is it is possible um to really create a
massive amount of energy from from
solar. you know the numbers if you talk
to your local model it's like there's
8,000 times more energy that hits the
surface of the earth than we consume as
a species. So being able to double
triple or 10x that is well within within
reach. Um See, you want to jump in
first?
>> A bunch of things to say here. First of
all, if you look at the difference
between that red and blue curve, it's
it's completely a copy of our old linear
versus exponential curves, right?
linears like this and exponential curves
up and we're on the wrong side of that
equation. Uh this is linear intuition
confronting an exponential curve. The
the problem is solar keeps getting
underestimated because people look at
install capacity today rather than the
vertical slope of the deployment curve.
And that's the nightmare. Uh and and
people can't get their heads around
this. This is such a a a kind of a an
old tired story that we should just get
past because China's advantage is not
like a magical solar panel. It's the
whole industrial system optimized around
manufacturing, the supply chain, the
permitting, the deployment. And in the
US, the big challenge is the
interconnection with the grid, the
transmission, the permitting speed,
right? And so you need all these
different you need nuclear, you need
solar, you need all of this. But battery
technology makes this a killer
opportunity because you can add a solar
panel today rather than wait 15 years
for some gigawatt scale energy project.
And so this is a massive opportunity
that's being left behind. If I was the
US I'd put a Manhattan type project into
perovsky and new solar capabilities
photonics have some huge opportunities
there and this when you have energy
abundance as I think we've all pointed
out that becomes a multiplier in every
other exponential technology. So this is
such a no-brainer and it really kind of
it's very dismaying to see the GDP
challenge here.
>> The GDP of a country is directly
proportional to the amount of energy
they create. And Alex that you know the
point you made about you know nuclear
being frozen it it's very clear here we
have not changed nuclear in you know you
know decades. We've still been producing
>> a half century something again I I think
in the fullness of time maybe 10 years
from now we'll have a better
understanding of what happened during
the 20th century that got screwed up
after World War II. But I I think
several things on the governance side
especially as they relate to nuclear
physics just in in the wake of World War
II. We went on the wrong path and my
hope is that it gets corrected.
>> Yeah. Uh Dave, do you want to make a
comment on this one? Well, I'll only
make one comment, which is, you know, on
that chart, the US is way behind in
solar. All those US panels are made in
China.
>> It's much worse than it looks.
>> Yeah. All right. Our next story is about
water. Uh the weather modification
startup called Rain Maker says that 10
drones uh that flew over Alaska's Kenai
Peninsula generated an estimated 19
million gallons of additional rainfall
in just 3 hours uh using what they call
a glacioenic cloud seating. So, you
know, ultimately weather modification is
no longer theoretical. It's here.
Applications for this kind of technology
include drought relief, agriculture,
wildfire prevention, and water security.
Uh, just for reference, um, you can look
it up. There's 3.4 quadrillion gallons
of water in the atmosphere. And
atmosphere capture is now a thing making
it in the clouds or capturing it on the
ground. So this is the abundance thesis
that predicts that water becomes
massively abundant when technology to
create it becomes cheap. And you know 10
drones creating 19 million gallons of
water in 3 hours is is pretty damn
cheap. Alex
>> and the the the drone part the UAV part
I think is especially novel. So imagine
a near-term future where we we achieve
our weather control grid. Not
necessarily. When I always go through
the mental exercise of how if I had to
build a global weather control system,
how would I do it? I think the easiest
way to do it is probably with reflectors
either terrestrially cheaper or in in
LEO a little bit more expensive. But
this points the way I think to a third
path for global weather control, which
is cloud seeding. Imagine a swarm, a
fleet of drones in the style of rain
makaker drones that are continuously in
flight, probably solar powered so they
can be permanently aloft and they are
just dispensing on an asneeded basis but
under the control of of some centralized
AI algorithm the particulates the the
nuclei needed for either snow or rain at
all informed by a global weather AI
model. We could in principle I think
with some further development of of
rainmakers technology and similar
technologies we could have total weather
control and that would be from a natural
disaster perspective. Imagine being able
to divert hurricanes
>> or disperse hurricanes before they form.
>> Yeah. Dis disperse with with
precipitation on the water instead of on
land or tornadoes, other extreme weather
events. Not to mention giving good
weather to the places that want it and
are willing to trade it. could have a
global weather trade where regions trade
each other for precipitation. There are
so many possibilities that are unlocked
by the confluence of AI, drones, and
weather modification. And now finally,
we're we're about to start this era of
geoengineering. I think
>> love it. I can see the business model
for rain maker. It's like you you know
different cities bid on where the drones
go.
>> Rain rain arbitrage. We could have a
global market for rain.
Uh, Salem,
>> rain becomes programmable. For for me,
the big breakthrough is not that they
made rain, which we've been able to do
for a while now, but it's the fact that
they could prove how much additional
rain they made that I think is really
interesting because it then unlocks a
huge amount of stuff. Weather, the
challenge is weather typically doesn't
respect weather boundaries. So trying to
figure out if you're downstream of
somebody that seated a bunch of clouds
and now you're not getting the rain and
they're getting it is going to create
some interesting tensions around that.
But this is exactly the type of
abundance technology, right? Allows you
to scale something really powerful. And
I think there's a there's a there's a
wonderful future. The business models
around geoengineering, as Alex puts it,
are pretty pretty rampant. You could do
some really interesting stuff. I mean
crop management, all sorts of thing
become capable. It's reminding me of one
of the more creative singularity
solutions that we ever saw was um at
Singularity University, one of the
summer students, I think his name was
Simon Daniels, had this idea of putting
platforms in the ocean that would spray
up waterway, take ocean water and spray
it up to block the sun from hitting the
earth and slowing down global warming
that way. and his business model to said
that was to do it along flight paths
where you could spray up water in the in
the shape of a Nike logo and sell that
advertising. Um, and so you sell do it
in the shape of certain patterns that
pays for the whole system at the same
time you lower the temperature into a
controllable way. And there's lots of
people that say, "Oh my god,
geoengineering is a bad thing. We don't
know the after effects." And the
counterpoint is well we've already been
geoengineering the world for 100 years
in a horrible uncontrolled unmeasurable
way and it's causing massive damage.
Look at the disaster in Nepal that's
happening right now. It's a complete
tragedy goes out to all [clears throat]
>> and nothing anybody could do in that
sense and you could avoid a lot of that
and so I think we it's incumbent upon us
to use technology to navigate this stuff
because you do it consciously rather
than unconsciously and that's the
powerful point. Welcome to the health
section of Moonshots brought to you by
Fountain Life. You know, my mission is
to help you use the latest technologies,
including AI, to not just do your work
at home, teach your kids, but to help
you live a long and healthy life. I'm
here today with an extraordinary
physician, the chief medical officer of
Fountain Life, Dr. Don Mucalem. Dawn,
let's talk about cancer. Uh, you know, I
know from the member database that we've
have at Fountain are members who come in
who think they're healthy. It turns out
3.3% of them have a cancer in their body
they don't know about.
>> That's right. You know, the majority of
cancers that we screen for, those aren't
the ones that are necessarily taking the
lives when found at a late stage. We
know that when cancer is found early,
the chances for cure are much higher. We
know it's much easier to treat a cancer
when found early versus when found late.
What we're finding in our members is
over 3.3% were found to have these
cancers that were otherwise wouldn't
have been found or detected.
>> Yeah. You know, it's interesting.
People, you don't feel the cancer until
stage three or stage four. And and if
you don't know what's going on inside
your body, it's like driving your car
with your eyes closed and you can know.
And so when members come through found,
how do they detect cancers?
>> So we're doing full body MRI and we also
do early cancer detection screening.
This is very very important. And these
are not typical tools used in the
conventional care setting when it comes
to prevention. This is a hard thing
because currently these are not studies
that insurance would yet be covering.
But the goal is to collect these
numbers, do the research, and work hard
to democratize wellness.
>> Yeah. So, at the end of the day, you can
know what's going on inside your body.
It's your obligation to know. So, check
out Fountain Life. You can go to
fountainlife.com/peter
to get access to the latest technology
to help you detect cancer at the very
beginning at stage one when it is
curable before it gets to stage three or
stage four in your world of hurt. All
right, let's move into the world of
health. Uh a couple of stories here.
First off, uh this week the FDA approved
a drug called uh let me pronounce this
properly. Duracanisib.
Duraxen rasib. It's the first RAS
inhibitor for metastatic pancreatic
adnocarcinoma
attacking the RA family of proteins that
drives tumor growth in most patients
with the disease. So pancreatic cancer I
mean is really considered almost a death
sentence. It's the most lethal least
treatable cancer for humans in history.
uh in uh previously treated metastatic
cancer uh durasib nearly doubled median
survival from 6.7 to 13.2 months. It
also tripled tumor response rates from
11% to 32%. And while this isn't a cure
and you know just getting an extra 7
months doesn't sound like a lot. That's
an additional 7 months for science to
continue to make more breakthroughs. I
mean that's the way I think about this
is like longevity escape velocity. Your
goal is to live long enough to get a
breakthrough to the another side. It's
also worth noting that RA mutations
drive about 30% of all human cancers. So
a drug that inhibits these proteins may
also be useful for other cancers as
well. Uh and you know we've heard this
said so many times by Daario, by Demis,
by many others. You know the goal is to
cure all these diseases including cancer
in this next decade. Alex, do you have a
take on this one?
>> Yeah. So, a couple of items. One, I
point out remarkably this is a daily
oral tablet. Pretty incredible.
Secondly, I'd point out I I was doing
some research on the the full uh lineage
as it were for duren rasib
involved in the development of this
drug. So, I think this is actually
finger to the wind. I think this is
probably slashh hopefully one of the
last generation of pancreatic cancer
medications that almost precedes the AI
wave. Uh and I I would expect lots of
new targets, lots of new approaches to
emerge from both the alphafold 3 style
of uh protein folding problem and
structural biology being solved as well
as virtual cell models. As far as I can
tell, Drax and Rasib used neither of
these in its design. It was like good
old-fashioned drug design, but I think
we're about to see a whole wave of
AIdriven drugs that take it from its
current response rate to, you know, near
100% using AI. And I I think that's to
be celebrated. I also want to celebrate
the FDA in approving this relatively
quickly. FDA noted that they approved
this I think 60 90 days something like
this prior to the due date which for
historic FDA speeds is actually pretty
remarkable speed. Yeah. So we're seeing
a much more I think responsive FDA that
now starts to care about basian versus
frequentist statistics that cares about
INDs quite a bit more it seems uh that's
interested in lowering the number of
clinical trials in exemplary cases.
Hopefully, this is I I think a baby step
towards a future where AI solves 5,000
diseases and then we have a regulatory
apparatus in the form of an FDA that is
able to metabolize all of those
innovations and turn them into cures.
>> Amen. Amen to that. Uh let me move to
our second story in the health corner
here. Uh this is published in nature
communications and it comes from an
international research team uh out of
University of Nottingham who developed a
biomimetic gel capable of repairing and
regrowing damaged tooth enamel. So this
is fluoridefree treatment uses lab
engineered proteins that mimic the
natural processes of enamel formation
during infancy. So as you might know you
know tooth enamel is the hardest
substance in the human body and it
doesn't regenerate. So until now, the
only thing you could do was replace
enamel with, you know, a synthetic
filling would eventually fail, you know.
So biomedic gel is an elastin-like
protein matrix designed to mimic the
natural protein scaffolding that
organizes enamel during tooth
development. The treatment didn't just
make something that looks like enamel.
It regenerated layers and restored
hardness, stiffness, water resistance,
friction properties resistant to
brushing, chewing, acid exposure in
labs. The gel acts like a scaffolding
that pulls calcium and phosphate from
the surrounding environment and directs
them into properly organizing minerals
rather than merely depositing an
amorphous coating. It's true enamel. I
mean, for me, this is huge. You know,
related oral disease affects, you know,
half the population. It's estimated at a
half a trillion dollars per year in
associated costs. You know, to put this
in perspective, this is still XVivo.
It's still done using extracted human
teeth and it's being done, you know,
effectively in the test tube of the
petri dish. Uh, but it's going to be
moving to human testing very quickly.
And as someone who's had poor dental
health and poor dental genetics all my
life, I couldn't be more excited about
this, especially for my kids. Um, Salem,
do you want to jump on this?
just fantastic. For me, the the big
thing is showing that the future of of
medicine is not like repairing broken
bits. It's convincing the body to
rebuild them and finding the mechanisms
and pathways, right? Uh and so this is
uh really really powerful stuff. It'll
completely change dentistry.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh this completely
>> people undervalue their oral health so
much, right? The mouth is a direct
corridor to the brain and to the heart.
You know, you need to be careful about
your oral health. Alex,
>> regenerative medicine. There's been a
future. We've been waiting for stuff
like this to happen for a long time.
It's great to see it finally kind of
actually come into being.
>> Alex, did you dig into this story, too?
>> I I did. I mean, I think these results
actually started bubbling up last year
first. I I'm incredibly interested in uh
materials engineering of human body,
human dental enamel included. But I I
think this was an AMA question that we
got in the the last pod episode. people
asking, yeah, like where's all the
innovation? Well, I I think the story um
uh which again like first started seeing
this uh last year um I I think this is
just one data point in a larger manifold
of just applying good old-fashioned
material science to the problem of human
teeth. uh and if if you can help to to
shape and engineer the pathways through
which tooth enamel grows, I have to
think that similar biioaterial
discoveries and inventions will also be
helpful for bone regrowth for a variety
of other key biomeaterials for
regenerative medicine. And again looking
at this the research behind this I saw
approximately no AI that that's always
my sniff test like how if and if and how
AI was used in this research and if it
wasn't used as appears to be the case
here there was approximately no AI as I
can see then take this but multiply it
by many orders of magnitude the sort of
progress I'd expect to see in a few
years in this area.
>> Dave how's your oral health?
Uh, it's fine. But, you know, I get I
get really excited about, you know, that
Madna story we had recently where
>> they had a melanoma vaccine that works
really well. Stock went way up. But what
was exciting is that it's a platform
that applies
>> to virtually any other cancer. And so,
when Alex says, "Yeah, these weren't
done with AI." I'm like, "Well, they're
really cool, but they're one-offs. I
can't wait for the repeatable. Like, I
can grow a tooth. I can grow an arm. I
can grow an ear. I can grow anything
now." And so then then you get into true
scalable regenerative medicine. I feel
like that's very very soon.
>> And by the way, by by the way, the work
on or on limb regrowth is is making
amazing progress.
>> Yeah. All right.
>> I think Dave, you're also touching on an
interesting almost like a singularity
flavored technological deflation story,
which is if there's no AI in it, like to
first order, what's the point? Uh either
infu either infuse it with AI and make
it scalable so that you can #solve
everything scale it up by a thousandx or
or just don't do it and do something
else that's higher leverage
>> not to discourage people from
regenerative medicine
>> sell your data to Dennis and Dennis will
AI what you just invented
>> that's perfect
>> all right finally let's jump into space
and robotic stories so the two first
stories are from the Elon universe uh
deote this week reported about the
potential lunar economy they put a
financial figure of 566 billion in
cumulative economic value by 2050. I
could not expect a low lower ball than
that number from uh uh from Deote. You
know the biggest early markets being
infrastructure costs, transportation,
power, comms, mobility, construction,
life support. They cite SpaceX as the
biggest winner because of the central
role that Starship will play. You know
clearly they are not taking into account
Alex manufacturing star mind on the moon
to fuel earth's
>> Disaphab pedophab is MIA.
>> Yeah. So you know just to put the
numbers on it cuz you know that number
you know half a trillion of lunar
economy may sound large but it's a
minuscule estimate. So Elon previously
stated his plans uh for Star Mine
started with about 100 to 200 gawatts
per year of orbital AI compute launched
from Earth and then moving to
manufacturing AI satellites on the moon
for launch with a mass driver. He
estimates that we could yield as much as
a 100 terowatts per year of orbital
compute uh based on lunar production
which would generate and and wait for it
an absurdly large amount of lunar
economy. Wait for it the estimate if
you're building a 100 terowatts per year
of orbital compute the economy would be
two quadrillion dollar per year of gross
revenue.
I mean, I I I like
>> I mean, I don't know, maybe Planetar is
is maybe too small,
>> two quadrillion dollars. I mean, now
we're now we're talking a a good
economy.
>> Um, but uh, you know, you know, Sem, you
deal with like the Deoites and the
Mckenzies and so these guys are so
conservative in their numbers all the
time. I mean,
>> crazy. Yeah, because there a there a lot
of them are accountants, so they're
scared of being called out for anything
vaguely approaching a real estimate. Uh
b they uh they want to make sure their
numbers are defensible to the nth
degree. So no speculation at all.
Whereas by definition, you're
speculating. So might might as well
speculate to some level of honesty. This
is the same type of pattern we've seen
before. By the way, one of these big
four, I won't say which one to protect
the innocent here, uh, put out an AI an
outentic AI report saying this is the
future of AI agents, etc. So, I
excitedly read it thinking I'd get some
in gloomerings that would give me some
sense of it. Except when I looked deeper
into it, the data they were using was 2
and a half years old. Okay? And how with
2 and 1/2 year old data you're going to
come up with anything about the agentic
world when everything happened in the
last 6 months? It's like how how do you
but they have so many checks and
balances and um and re internal review
systems that that dilute everybody's
thinking careful you can't say that da
da d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d
d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d d
d that by the time it comes out it's
been whitewashed so many times it's mean
>> lawyers and and and cross reference
checkers of even more cautious people
and and then nothing it's nothing
realistic gets put out in general I
typically say take any of their
estimates and multiply it by 10 or 20
times
Huh. Dave, what's your thought?
>> We had the Deote AI team in here in the
office the other day. They're very, very
good actually. But they were Yeah, they
were also saying the same thing about
the accounting side. So So Liam, you're
confirmed from inside Deote. Um, yeah,
quadrillions of dollars. That's what
Elon was talking about. I I believe it
because uh the gravity well is the key.
You know, Peter, you talk about this a
lot, but everyone's like, "Why would I
bother manufacturing that on the moon?
What's the point? You know, I can just
make it here." Like, no, no, it's the
gravity. Well,
>> you start building power plants based on
just lunar minerals and
>> all of a sudden you're like, this is so
much more efficient. Plus, you know,
there's no worry about pollution and
stuff like that.
>> Yeah, lunar regalith is silicon. What's
that used for? Oh, okay. Power
generation, aluminum, nickel, iron, and
oxygen. I mean, it's like the perfect
materials for building Dyson swarms.
Alex, I've got to feed it to you to sort
of uplevel this vision here.
Well, the the moon may not be a harsh
mistress. She may be a wealthy mistress
at this point. I I I do think the
pedophab is the killer app for the moon.
I I don't think it's tourism. I don't
think it's transporter infra or comms.
>> The Apollo program was sort of
infamously, arguably a successor to the
Manhattan project. And I I think to the
extent that the the full history of the
Apollo program is already fully
understood and and in the public record,
I think a relative failure. I I would
love to see the moon reach its full
economic potential. And I I just don't
think that is going to happen anyway
other than full private development. And
right now it does appear that the
critical path is mining chips, fabbing
data centers on the moon. It's not rods
from God. It's not uh deploying US NASA
astronauts to the moon. That's all well
and good and everything. And friend of
the pod Jared is I I think doing an
amazing job of reinvigorating the case
on the government side for vision
reactors on the moon and all of that.
But I I think in the fullness of time
even that just ends up being a rounding
error compared to data center deployment
and mining on the moon. Unless I don't
know unless 2001 of space odyssey
happens and we discover some monoliths
on the moon in which case that's the
killer optab
or the exop on the moon is it's really
interesting to game it out because when
you when you look at the fab
construction process you know a lot of
the components in there are just routine
aluminum routine you know just
construction there are a few really
critical pieces that you can still make
on earth and launch them and it'll be
just a tiny fraction of the total cost
but you know once you start
manufacturing chips on the moon, the
solar panels on the moon. I mean, it's
just exponential takeoff from there. And
you know, the technology is just not
that far away.
>> The problem is that these guys are not
looking at uh what the you can't ask
what the lunar economy is today. You
have to say what industries become
unlocked when the cost of moving mass
off the earth drops by an order or two
of magnitude. And that's the imagination
gap.
>> Yeah. And and I just want to say a shout
out to Jared Isaacman who's a friend of
the pod and you know what an
extraordinary administrator. I could not
be more proud. I said it during our
podcast with him. I've known I think all
the administrators pretty well over the
last 40 50 years or 40 years. Uh and uh
he is by far the best most eloquent most
visionary most business-minded. Um, and
he is an accelerationist and if
anybody's going to support humanity, uh,
you know, moving beyond the bounds of
Earth, uh, it's it's him.
>> Peter, like, every time the CCP sponsors
an influence op to deter American
terrestrial data centers, the lunar
pedophab gets its wings.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
All right. Our second Elon story comes
from Tesla. The company announced it's
expanded its rollout of cyber cabs in
Texas. Uh they just registered 79 Model
Y's for the robo taxi service. Um and
this is starting to look more, you know,
less like an experiment and more like a
real fleet. In Las Vegas alone, Tesla
recently said it's going to be deploying
2500 vehicles in the next year. It's
Cyber Cab. Uh Tesla's official long-term
milestone is to reach a million robo
taxis in commercial operations as soon
as possible. And if you do the
estimates, uh, that's probably about a
hundred billion dollars of revenue in
ride share revenue for Tesla. Let's take
a look at a quick video here just to
remind people how cool, uh, the cyber
cab is. Um, I have to say, you know, I I
love Google, but you know, Whimo's new
vehicle is kind of clunky. This is
pretty beautiful.
This is Elon at the original Cyber Cab
roll out. I love those doors.
>> Way cooler than I thought.
>> Yeah, those are uh those are three
Commodores or four Commodores.
Pretty cool.
>> Yeah, such a great design.
>> It's a beautiful design. it and in gold
is like it's perfect.
>> It really is. At the Gigafactory,
remember they had that one that was all
exploded out so you could see inside all
the parts. It's just a beautiful
beautiful design and it doesn't have
that many moving parts, you know, so you
can see how they're going to manufacture
them at an incredible scale.
>> Yeah. Uh
>> you know, just a just for a consu from a
consumer point of view, [clears throat]
all my friends that are driving the new
full self-driving uh Model Y's are like,
"Oh my god, this is life-changing. I
literally go anywhere FSD and the wait
list right now is about 3 months for a
Model Y but 3 months from today the
fully engaging you want to talk to it
all the time AI will be everywhere. So,
you might want to get on that wait list
because you're going to want to be
talking to your AI and continuing your
dialogue with your
>> roof,
>> you know, uh it's going to be amazing.
And, you know, for if there are
entrepreneurs out there when the cyber
cap comes out, you know, buy a hundred
of them, put them out to work and we'll
have a fleet of cyber cabs generating
revenue for you. I think that's going to
be an incredible business. I I I will
say I I love my Tesla Model Y 2026
Juniper Launch Series Edition. It it is
life-changing. The FSD is incredible.
The the manufacturing quality of the car
is incredible. I can't wait for Cyber
Cabs and robo taxis in general to come
to Boston. I'll beat the drum once more
for the broken Whimo's theory of if a
city can't accommodate robo taxis, then
it is not equipped for the singularity.
And hopefully someone from the city of
Boston is listening to this and
scratching their head and wondering just
what is doing with Boston and why Boston
doesn't have proper Whimo support. If if
you're scratching your head and you're
in a position of authority, call Dave or
call me. We'd love to figure this out.
>> Yeah. The same thing when Uber was made
when Uber was made illegal in France. I
was like, "Okay, if you're an
entrepreneur, don't move to France."
It's it's like these are telltale signs
of what cities are on the singularity
curve and which are not.
>> Yeah.
>> See,
>> um uh I'm actually having to sell my
beloved 10-year-old Tesla Model S to get
a Model Y because I need the FSD.
>> Uh I'll send a photograph of it in for
our next pod just so everybody can see I
totally love my car. But this is a big
big deal. I think for a couple of
reasons. One is uh there's three things
here. One is that this changes from
purchasing a car to autonomous revenue
miles. Uh what's the cost per autonomous
revenue per mile, right? And if you can
do it at a decent safety adjusted cost,
this is actually massive. The uh the
fleet growth will lower weight times
which will improve the US user extreme
experience which will uh increase the
rise. It generates more data which will
create that inner loop that Alex is
talking about. So I think there's some
really amazing downstream benefits from
all of this. It totally changes again
insurance and and cleaning up and
charging all sorts of I think you'll
turn gas stations into autonomous car
cleaning depots. That kind of thing will
start to happen. Um but uh for me the
big one is I made a bet. I got up on
stage 10 years ago and I said, "My kid
will never get a driver's license and
I've got just about a year for this
cyber cab to roll out to get out there
before before he he may get one anyway
just to get away from the parents, but
he wouldn't have to." And then I'll be
proven correct. So important not to lose
your credibility as a futurist.
>> Yeah. You know, the this abundant story
here is the poorest people in the planet
will be driven around by electric
autonomous vehicles. Yes,
>> it will be the cheapest mode of
transportation.
>> And think about the elderly, right? And
people that can't get around easily and
all and and and and it's just the market
suddenly becomes so magical delivering
huge capability to segments of the
population that can't do it today. Huge.
>> Yeah. I'm going to put up this uh image
here. I I I love it. Just comparing uh
Cyber Cab and and Whimo. Uh and you know
I I have to say
I don't know how Whimo is going to
compete when Cyber Cab rolls out. You
know first of all CyberCap is eight
cameras. Again Elon made the point that
if humans can just drive with one or two
eyes you should be able to have a car do
it with just cameras and uh compared to
the LAR and radars and 13 cameras that
uh that the Whimo has. And I think the
point with the brains on this image is
CyberCab is is massively AIdriven. Um
yeah, I could not agree more.
>> It's going to be a big fight um to this.
By the way, didn't um Tesla acknowledge
that cameras aren't enough in this?
>> No, I don't think so. Tesla does use for
short range, it uses ultrasound, but
everyone uses ultrasound. It does not
use LAR. Uh I I think there's sort of an
interesting maybe [clears throat]
speaking prospectively not financial
advice epitap in so far as Luminar the
LAR provider declared bankruptcy uh half
a year ago at at this point but I if I
had to bet again not investment advice I
think the market abhores monopolies and
I think there's probably room for at
least a handful of competing five or 10
of them there will be many of these
around competing beating themselves up
and lowering throwing the price across
the b across
>> and we all win.
>> Yeah. I introduced Austin Russell, the
the CEO of Luminar before it went out of
business to Elon at a party and uh and I
watched them duke it out on whether LAR
was important. Anyway, it was a it was a
fun show and Elon was like, "No way. Not
interested. Not going to go there." All
right, our final story. Uh it's a little
bit of a bizarre one but expected uh in
the direction in the world of robotics.
A company called Somnia Lab has built a
robot for intimacy and the internet has
lost its mind. It's called Model L.
Maybe L for love. It's 5 foot n inches,
44 pound robot with 24 degrees of
freedom with the warmth simulation,
touch response, and preference memory
designed for human robot sexual
encounters. Okay, it's finally here,
guys. So, real humans wear motion
capture suits. I'm going to show you a
video of that in a moment to record 165
intimate actions that were fed into the
model. Somnia Lab is taking $300
deposits for delivery in late 2027. What
makes the model L more interesting than
a sophisticated sex doll is the attempt
to combine physical embodiment,
persistent AI memory, and
personalization. Somnia says the robot
is intended to remember conversations
and preferences across encounters, learn
a user's rhythms, [laughter] can't make
this stuff up, and communication style.
Uh, the body is made from lightweight
carbon fiber with modular skin and
structural components designed to be
serviced and upgraded. Customers will be
able to customize the face, the makeup,
the eyes, the skin appearance, and the
body silhouette. So, I guess this is a
story around uh abundance of intimacy.
Let's take a look at this.
>> This was inevitable. Peter, I'm waiting
for you to say fully functional,
programmed in multiple techniques.
[laughter]
>> No, I'm not going to go there.
>> Not yet.
>> Let's watch this video. This is a video
of the motion capture uh being done to
train the AI models here.
with cheesy music to boot. We
>> We We've hit a We've hit a new high
here. This is incredible. [laughter]
>> One has to admire the the low degree of
freedom. Like that was a pretty simple
face. I think we were seeing that was a
that was a human in a mocap suit, right?
>> It was. It was.
>> That was low quality in every way from
the music to the [laughter] video to
everything.
>> A robot porn video. Oh my god. You know,
you combine this with the uh
conversation we had earlier about AI
girlfriends and boyfriends, right? And
the human, you know, relationship is
cooked.
>> You think I mean I I go back and forth.
Is there going to be an app store for
for moap movements or is this just going
to be pre-training or post-raining data
for a foundation model that knows about
everything?
>> I want to see the job ad for that one.
[laughter]
>> I have a couple of comments on this one.
>> Please. So the first thing is you know
this type of embodied AI has really a
pretty difficult data problem right
because you can scrape the internet for
text there's no internet scale data set
or physical human interaction all
>> you talking about internet [laughter]
are you looking at hold on hold on hold
on in terms of the the physical movement
etc so the the what I love more than
anything here is the economic approach
right you you crowdsource the You do
crowdfunding of the early thing, get
early customer and then use the customer
demand to finance the hardware and
generate the interaction data as you
scale the product. This is like a pretty
classic EXO flywheel. So I thought that
was you got a new career out of you. You
got it all inside.
>> Now I'll give a hot take hot take on the
hot sheets which is I I don't actually
think this is that promising as an
approach. There is an abundance of
evidence at this point that you can do a
great job either pre-training or
post-training robots for more call them
economically productive applications
just from watching videos without any
need for human mocap at all. So, if I
had to guess, my guess is this is like a
very 2026 story with people mocapping
sex maneuvers from like manually, but it
doesn't scale nearly as well as just
pre-training off of internet video is my
guess.
>> Okay, circle of trust here. How many
have you ordered, guys? [laughter]
>> I won't tell anybody. Oh my god.
>> We we need guests and panelists that are
in their like 20s for that.
>> Oh my god. Dave, any any closing
thoughts on this topic?
>> None whatsoever, actually, as it turns
out. First time in my life. Nothing to
add. Sorry. Speechless.
>> My god. All right, everybody. Uh, I want
to say that's a wrap, but we do have a
closing video. Um, if you have outro
music videos, please send them to
mediadmandis.com. We love sharing them.
We love the creativity of our community.
>> And we'll see you guys in four weeks to
the day.
>> Yes. at Moonshots live in LA se the
evening of September 24th and all day on
September 25th.
>> You can go to moonshots.com to uh to
apply. It is by application. Uh and it's
going to be an amazing community for you
to network with and spend the day with
all five of us. The you know the
moonshots quintent will be there. Uh you
get a chance to grill Alex uh Sem and uh
and of course Dave. It's going to be
it's going to be awesome. All right,
let's play this video by Ellen uh
Vamman. Thank you, Ellen, for your
submission.
[music]
[music] Heat.
Heat.
[music]
>> [singing]
>> Nice heroic music, gentlemen.
>> It's the Lord of the Rings in space
mashup. I never knew I wanted.
[laughter]
>> H That was fun, guys. Really loved it. A
lot of fascinating stories and
definitely one bizarre one.
>> Until we see you again twice next week
for another episode recording.
>> Be well.
>> Can't wait. We'll try and sleep in the
middle. God help us all.
>> Live long and prospire as they say.
>> Likewise. All right. [laughter]
Take care, folks.
[music]